<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dialogue (or familiar discourse) and conference betweene the husbandman and fruit-trees in his nurseries, orchards, and gardens wherein are discovered many usefull and profitable observations and experriments [sic] in nature, in the ordering fruit-trees for temporall profitt ... / by Ra. Austen ...</title>
            <author>Austen, Ralph, d. 1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5888</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12192027</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12192027</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55886</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26231)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55886)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 119:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dialogue (or familiar discourse) and conference betweene the husbandman and fruit-trees in his nurseries, orchards, and gardens wherein are discovered many usefull and profitable observations and experriments [sic] in nature, in the ordering fruit-trees for temporall profitt ... / by Ra. Austen ...</title>
                  <author>Austen, Ralph, d. 1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 87 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Hen. Hall for Thomas Bowman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Princeton University Library.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: several pages, including t.p., mutilated.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fruit-culture --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DIALOGV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (OR FAMILIAR DISCOURS<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and conference betweene the <hi>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN</hi> and <hi>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES;</hi> in his <hi>Nurſeries, Orchards,</hi> and <hi>Gardens.</hi> Wherein are diſcovered many uſefull, and profitable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Experriments in Nature, in the Ordering of <hi>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES,</hi> for temporall profitt; Improving alſo the ſame to higher ends, and uſes, in Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all things, for the Good, and profitt of all; both in the Church, and of the World. Whereby the Wiſdome, Power, Bounty, and goodneſſe of God to his Glory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are clearely ſeen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and read, in this Volume of the <hi>Creatures;</hi> And all men inſtructed by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, in their Duty towards God, in order to their Comfort, Edification, and Salvation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>RA: A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STEN;</hi> Practiſer (50 years) in the Art of Planting <hi>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Cant. 2.3.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>As the Appletree among the Trees of the wood, ſo is my beloved among the Sonnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſate downe under his ſhaddow with great delight; And his Fruit was ſweete to my tast.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hoſe. 12.10.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have uſed ſimilitudes by the Miniſtrie of the Prophets.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Aquin.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Tunc homo creaturas interrogat; quando <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s dil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>genter conſiderat: ſed tunc interrogatae reſpondent, cum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mo perſpicit quod tanta ordinatio eſſe non poſſit, niſi ab <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>qua ſuperiore ſapientia diſpenſante:</p>
            </q>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed by <hi>Hen: Hall.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Bowman</hi> 167<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE to the READER.</head>
            <p>GOD hath given to man two great Books, to read and ſtudy; <hi>viz:</hi> His workes, and his word; whereby we may come to know God, and learn our Duty to him. The Creatures of God do all of them ſpeake out the Praiſes of God; and are not only Examples to us of Obedience, but alſo do call aloude unto Man, and inſtruct, and teach him, what he ought to do; And that as plainly and convincingly to the mind, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as words do to the eare: The Prophet ſaith: <hi>Pſ:</hi> 19.1, 2. <hi>&amp;c. The heavens declare the glory of God, and the Firmament ſheweth his handy worke: ver:</hi> 2. <hi>Day unto Day uttereth ſpeech; and night unto night ſheweth knowledge: ver:</hi> 3. <hi>There is no ſpeech, nor Language,
<pb facs="tcp:55886:5"/> Where their voice is not heard. ver.</hi> 4. <hi>Their line is gon out through all the Earth, and their words to the Ends of the world.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> recites words to the ſame purpoſe; <hi>Rom:</hi> 10:18: <hi>ſhewing that all men have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions to know God, even by his works. Have they not heard</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Yes verily, their ſound went into all the Earth, and their words to the Ends of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſee here, <hi>inanimate creatures</hi> can ſpeake to the praiſe of God, and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of man: The <hi>excellencies, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite perfections of God,</hi> are plainly ſeen, and read <hi>perspeculum creaturarum;</hi> even in the Creatures which he hath made; And men that are illiterate, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not read a line in any printed Book, may yet read diſtinctly, and plainly in this Book of the Creatures if they will but ſet their <hi>Reaſon and underſtanding</hi> on work, and learn their <hi>Language,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:55886:5"/> the manner of Diſcourſe with them, Inanimate creatures, ſuch as are but bare. And naked ſubſtances without life, or ſence, as the <hi>heavens, the Sun, Moon, and Starrs,</hi> yet even theſe do <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare knowledge, and wiſdome;</hi> to Man: they have a <hi>ſpeech, a voice;</hi> their <hi>words</hi> go the ends of the world; to every <hi>Nation, and Language;</hi> And men who have not the Scriptures, nor any other Books, or writings of men, they ſhall not be excuſed in their ignorance of God, and of their dutie to him; if they learne not from his creatures; if they underſtand not their <hi>speech, and Language,</hi> and learn not from them; And this is plain from Rom: 1, 20. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of the heathen, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving them for their ignorance, and diſobedience; he tells them, much of God may be ſeen, and known, in and by the Creatures: <hi>The inviſible things of God, from the Creation of the world,
<pb facs="tcp:55886:6"/> are clearly ſeen being underſtood by the things that are made, even his Eternall Power, and Godhead; ſo that they are left without excuſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Attributes of God;</hi> (his <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Power, goodneſſe, love, and bounty,</hi> towards mankind) are clearly ſeene, read, and underſtood, by the things that he hath made. And let not men think, that becauſe they are not Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in any School Learning, therefore they ſhall be excuſed. Though they are ignorant of God, and of their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to him: for the Prophet tells ſuch what they ſhall find, if they are of the number of thoſe <hi>ſottiſh children, that have no underſtanding: he that made them will not have Mercy on them; and he that formed them will ſhew them no Favour: Iſay</hi> 27:11: So that it highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes every one to learn the <hi>Language of the Creatures;</hi> and how to <hi>conferre, and diſcourſe with them</hi> for their profitt,
<pb facs="tcp:55886:6"/> and edification: And among the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures with <hi>Fruit-trees.</hi> the ſubject of the Enſuing <hi>Dialogue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shall men plant <hi>Orchards, and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of Fruit-trees,</hi> and only take their <hi>Pleaſures, and Profits</hi> from them, from year to year: This is no more than the <hi>Beaſts, and the Birds</hi> do; They ſitt under their ſhade in the heate of Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and eat of their Fruits: The <hi>Swine</hi> gathers, and eates the Fruits that fall under the Trees, and goes his way, but underſtands not whence they are; but men that are endued with Reaſon, and underſtanding (eſpecially if a <hi>Principle of ſupernaturall grace,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> be dwelling, and ruling in them) muſt look higher, and make another uſe of <hi>Fruit-trees,</hi> than meerly for <hi>temporall Profit, and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures:</hi> Men muſt <hi>diſcourſe with Fruit-trees,</hi> having learned to underſtand <hi>their Language</hi> which though it be nor
<pb facs="tcp:55886:7"/> Articulate, and diſtinct to the <hi>outward ſence of hearing,</hi> in the ſound of words, yet they ſpeake plainly, and diſtinctly to the <hi>inward ſence, the underſtanding:</hi> The ſoul hath its <hi>ſences,</hi> as well as the body; the ſoul doth really <hi>hear, ſee</hi> &amp;c. as well as the body: ſo that we may learn from Fruit-trees many good leſſons, and uſefull inſtructions; they being Creatures, that are alwaies ſpeaking, and alwaies ſpeake the truth, both for the glory of God, and the good of men;</p>
            <p>Every Creature ſpeakes this aloude to every man, <hi>qui fecit me, propter te, fecit te, propter ſe: he that made me, for thee, made thee for himſelfe:</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Caryl</hi> in his expoſition upon <hi>Job,</hi> Chap. 12. ſpeakes much to this purpoſe: <hi>All Creatures,</hi> (as he there ſaies) <hi>have a teaching voyce; they read us divinity Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of Divine Providence. Seculum, eſt Speculum:</hi> The world below is a
<pb facs="tcp:55886:7"/> Glaſs, wherein we may ſee the world above, they who cannot read other Books, may yet run, and read this Book of the Creatures, written in great, and plain Letters, and Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters. <hi>Non eſt ullum animalculum tam exiguum in quo non plus diſcere poſsimus, quam in omnibus ſculptis, pictis, aut ſimulachris,</hi> Lauac.</p>
            <p>The <hi>idle, ſlothfull man</hi> is ſent to the <hi>Piſmire,</hi> to learn and be inſtructed, <hi>Pro:</hi> 6.6. <hi>Go to the Ant thou ſluggard, conſider her wayes, and be wiſe, ſhe getteth her meat in the Summer</hi> &amp;c: ſuch as provide not in <hi>ſummer,</hi> for <hi>Winter,</hi> in <hi>youth</hi> for <hi>old age,</hi> in <hi>this life</hi> for <hi>the next,</hi> are condemned by this little Creature; <hi>Deus maximus in minimis:</hi> God is ſeen in the leaſt of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: yea, go to the <hi>Oxe,</hi> and the <hi>Aſſe,</hi> thou brutiſh, ſenſual man, or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, conſider, and learn of them: They know, and own, ſerve, and
<pb facs="tcp:55886:8"/> obey, their Maſter, him that feedeth them; <note place="margin">Iſay: 1.3. The Oxe knoweth his owner and the Aſſe his Maſters Crib; but Iſrael hath not known Me, ſaith the Lord.</note> but thou (as thou wanteſt grace, ſo alſo thou wanteſt the good Nature, that theſe poor Creatures have, and ſhew forth to him that keeps them; Thou art fed, and clothed dayly, and haſt all things convenient for life from the hand of God, and yet thou ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt him not, but ſerveſt thy ſelf, and rebelleſt againſt God: therefore theſe dull Beaſts ſhall condemn thee.</p>
            <p>Let not men make light of theſe things (of <hi>learning from Fruit-trees, and other Creatures</hi>) they ſhall find one day, (and that ſhortly too) they ſhall be called to an Account; and be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Creatures,</hi> as well as by the <hi>word:</hi> Therefore it concernes every one to learn their ſpeech, and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and to be inſtructed thereby, in order to their <hi>own Duty,</hi> and the <hi>glory of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:8"/>
            <p>O the loud cry, and voyce of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure from theſe very Creatures, (of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he infinite <hi>wiſdome, Power, and bounty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f God</hi> towards Man,) how is it heard, plainly, and diſtinctly, not only in the infinite number, and kinds of <hi>Fruit-trees, Flowers, and vegetables in Orchards, and Gardens,</hi> but alſo in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very individuall, and particular Tree: Conſider only, but one large <hi>Apple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ree;</hi> ſome of them bearing many Buſhels of Fruits in one year; Every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>articular Fruit hath ſeverall ſeeds, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ernels in it; and every ſeed (though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>any thouſands from one Tree) hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e Nature of the whole Tree in it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>lf, and that exacty: <hi>Potentially,</hi> the whole tree; in that ſmall ſubſtance; (many of them leſſe then a graine of Wheat) it hath in it the <hi>innate, intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall forme, and vertue of the VVhole Tree,</hi> that huge, and vaſt body that we ſee above ground, and will (if
<pb facs="tcp:55886:9"/> ſowen) produce the ſame in kind: And not only ſo, but likewiſe every <hi>ſmall Twigg</hi> of the Tree, yea, the <hi>least bud of the leaſt twigg</hi> hath alſo <hi>(virtually)</hi> the whole tree in it ſelf, and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the ſame, if inoculated, according to Art.</p>
            <p>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſten</hi> takes notice of theſe things and admires God in them; <note place="margin">Gen: ad lit: ch 15.</note> and exhorts all men to ſtudy them, and learn from them; <hi>Ex ipſis operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus dei indagare conemur; conſideremus ergo, cujuſlibet Arboris pulcritudinem, in robore, ramis, frondibus, Pomis; &amp;c. illud germen ex ſemine; in ſemine ergo illa omnia fuerunt primitus; non mole corporeae magnitudinis, ſed vipotentiaque cauſaliter: in exiguo grano mirabilior prostantior que vis eſt, quia valuit adia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens humor commixtus terrae, quid enim ex arbore illâ, ſurgit, aut pendet, quod non ex quodam occulto Theſauro ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis illius extractum atque depromptum eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Job</hi> exhorts us to learn from theſe, and all Creatures; <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.7, 8.9. <hi>&amp;c. Aske now the Beasts, and they ſhall teach thee, and the Foules of the Air and they ſhall tell thee: Or speake to the earth, and it ſhall teach thee; or</hi> (as it is tranſlated) <hi>ſpeake to every Twigg, or Tree that growes upon the Earth, and it ſhall teach thee; And the Fiſhes of the Sea, ſhall declare unto thee.</hi> Here we ſee, are many Maſters, and Teachers, for the inſtruction of Man, in his duty to God; Chriſtians that have not only Reaſon, but grace, may learn from Creatures that have neither Reaſon, nor ſence; Grace in the heart of a Chriſtian, improves common, earthly Objects, to ſpiritual uſes, and holy Ends: it is (ſpiritually) the <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers ſtone;</hi> that turnes <hi>Earth, into Heaven; Naturall Objects, into Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual,</hi> As faith ſees him that is inviſible, and things that are not ſeen, ſo <hi>ſence</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:55886:10"/> ſhewes us him that is iniſible, i. e. God in his workes. Being as a proſpective Glaſſe through which we may ſee the lively ſpecies of infinit ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies in God.</p>
            <p>Firſt, All Creatures yeild ready Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God; for they obey the Law of their Creation: <hi>Fire, and Haile, Snow, and vapors, Stormy winds and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, fulfilling his word. Pſ.</hi> 148.8.</p>
            <p>Secondly, And as Creatures teach us <hi>Obedience to God,</hi> in obſerving the Law of their Creation; ſo alſo they teach us <hi>dependance upon God:</hi> as we ſee <hi>Hoſe</hi> 2.21. God having betrothed Iſrael his people, <hi>in righteouſneſse, in judgment, in loving kindneſſe, in mercies, in Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe,</hi> and that for ever; from that time all the Creatures do ſtrive to do them good; but yet in a Chain of <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pendance;</hi> Every one confeſſing their in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ability, without help from God: Iſrael had need of the Creatures to nouriſh
<pb facs="tcp:55886:10"/> them, They cry to God for <hi>Corne, VVine, and Oyle;</hi> Theſe are ready, and willing to nouriſh <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but then the <hi>Earth</hi> muſt bring them forth, therefore theſe cry to the <hi>Earth,</hi> to give them rooting, and nouriſhment, the <hi>Earth</hi> would do this willingly, for <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſake, but cannot, except the <hi>Heavens</hi> do water it, with <hi>Rain,</hi> and <hi>Dewes;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Earth</hi> cryes to the <hi>Heavens,</hi> but the <hi>Heavens</hi> (though willing) can give no <hi>Rain,</hi> nor refreſhing, until <hi>God</hi> command them to do it; therefore the <hi>Heavens</hi> cry unto <hi>God,</hi> that he would give them Commiſſion to <hi>water the Earth:</hi> As we ſee: <hi>Hoſe:</hi> 2.2. <hi>I will hear (ſaith the Lord) I will hear the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and they ſhall hear the Earth, and the Earth ſhall hear the Corne, and the VVine, and the Oyle, and they ſhall heare Iſrael:</hi> So God commanding the <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi> the <hi>heavens</hi> feed the <hi>Earth,</hi> and the <hi>Earth</hi> feeds the <hi>Corn, VVine, and Oyl,</hi> and theſe feed <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:11"/>
            <p>The eyes of all Creatures waite up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, and he giveth them their meate in due ſeaſon: <hi>Pſ.</hi> 145.15. <hi>he feedeth the young Ravens that call upon Him: Pſ.</hi> 147.9. <hi>The Lyons roaring after their Prey, do ſeeke their Meate of God:</hi> So they all teach us the ſame Leſſon of <hi>dependance upon God for all neceſſaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſhewes us, That there is ſomewhat even in <hi>inanimate Creatures,</hi> that puts forth an Act of <hi>Expectation,</hi> yea, of <hi>Earneſt Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> for delivera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage that the ſin of man hath brought them under; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19. <hi>The earneſt expectation of the Creature, waiteth for the manifeſtation of the ſons of God: and ver.</hi> 22. <hi>The whole Creation growneth, and travelleth in pain together until now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly: We may alſo learn this Leſſon from the Creatures (even from <hi>irrationall, and lifeleſſe Creatures</hi>) not
<pb facs="tcp:55886:11"/> only (as was ſaid 1: <hi>Obedience to God, and</hi> 2: <hi>dependance upon him;</hi> but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe 3ly. to deſire, and long, for a full <hi>freedome, and deliverance</hi> from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of Corruption, and to attain the Glorious liberty of the ſons of God; for ſhall <hi>inanimate Creatures</hi> do this; and ſhall not <hi>Rational, and Spiritual Chriſtians</hi> do it, much more.</p>
            <p>Now if any one ask this Queſtion; how may we <hi>ſpeake to Fruit-trees,</hi> or any other Creatures that are without <hi>Reaſon or ſence,</hi> that we may receive Inſtructions from them.</p>
            <p>This Queſtion (long ſince) is anſwered by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſten;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">10: Book of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions.</note> 
               <hi>I put the Queſtion</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to the Earth, and to the Sea; and to the rest of the Creatures; and they give me an Anſwer; Now if you would know what my Queſtion was; It was the deep intention, and conſideration, I had in my heart, about the Creatures; And would
<pb facs="tcp:55886:12"/> you know what their Anſwer was; their Anſwer was that which I collected in my Meditations, from their ſeveral Natures, qualities, and properties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that to <hi>confer, and diſcourſe with Fruit-trees</hi> (as in the enſuing <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lougue</hi>) and to receive inſturctions from them, not only as to <hi>temporall Profits,</hi> but <hi>Spiritual</hi> alſo, it is, in a Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, ſerious, and Spiritual man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to <hi>conſider them, and dive, and ſearch into their Natures, and Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;</hi> as we may obſerve, and gather by Experience, from year, to year, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them; which every Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall man may do, more, or leſſe; But yet the more knowledg, and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence any man has, the better it is don; And then the making of <hi>right conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, upon ſuch Conſiderations,</hi> thoſe are the <hi>Anſweres, Teachings, or inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Fruit-trees;</hi> ſo of all other Creatures, (as was ſaid;) <hi>Job:</hi> 12.7.
<pb facs="tcp:55886:12"/> 
               <hi>aske the Beaſts, and they ſhall teach thee; docebit te, unaquaque ex Bestiis docebit te.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Excellencies, Vertues, beauties and perfections</hi> that are in the Creatures do plainly ſhew forth, and manifeſt, the <hi>infinite Excellencies and perfections of God;</hi> his <hi>VViſdom, Power, Goodneſs, Beauty, Bounty &amp;c.</hi> Now, when we diligently conſider, and ſearch out their <hi>Natures and Vertues, Beauties, and Properties,</hi> which God hath Stampt upon them, and put into them, and make <hi>right Concluſions,</hi> then we <hi>confer and diſcourſe</hi> with them; The Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures diſcover the <hi>Attributes</hi> of God to the <hi>Eye,</hi> as his word does to the <hi>Ear,</hi> and both to the <hi>Mind.</hi> And this produceth (or ſhould do) in every one, <hi>Praiſe, and Glory to God, wonder, and admiration of him;</hi> for that he is the <hi>Creator, and contriver</hi> of all theſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent things: who being the <hi>Originall
<pb facs="tcp:55886:13"/> and first Cauſe</hi> of all theſe <hi>wonderful, and excellent Creatures,</hi> ſo many, ſo good, ſo beautifull, ſo uſefull, profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and pleaſant, in the lives of men, it muſt needs be concluded, that he himſelf is much more ſo, in himſelfe; yea, infinitely above, better, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding them all, and conſequently to be <hi>deſired, and loved above them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Aquin:</note> 
               <hi>Hujuſmodi interrogatio eſt mentis ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio, qua creaturarum perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones intuemur: Tunc homo Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turas interrogat, quando eas diligenter conſiderat; ſed tunc interrogate reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, cum homo proſpicit quod tanta or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinatio eſse non poſsit, niſi ab aliqua ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periore ſapientia diſpenſante.</hi> That is: When we <hi>ſeriouſly conſider, the nature, and properties</hi> of inanimate creatures; then we <hi>aske Queſtions</hi> of them; and they being thus Queſtioned, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn <hi>an anſwer</hi> unto men, when we clearly perceive that their wonderfull
<pb facs="tcp:55886:13"/> 
               <hi>Natures, vertues, and properties,</hi> cannot be, but from the <hi>Power, and VViſdome of a ſuperior Cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Every <hi>created being,</hi> inſtructs us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our <hi>Creator,</hi> of <hi>his wiſdom, and goodneſſe,</hi> and of our <hi>duty, and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe</hi> we owe unto him; ſo that as many <hi>Creatures</hi> as are in the world, ſo many <hi>Teachers</hi> there are in the world: Therefore none ſhall be excuſed at the laſt day, for their <hi>ignorance of God;</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we have not only <hi>the word of God,</hi> but <hi>all the Creatures of God</hi> to inſtruct us; concerning God and our duty to him. So then; with theſe breife inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions concerning <hi>diſcourſe with Fruit-trees,</hi> I commit the Enſuing <hi>Dialogue</hi> to thy uſe, for thy profitt. Who am thy Friend to ſerve thee in love.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>RA: AVSTEN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:14"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:14"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Trees Speake to men.</hi> pag. 1.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Language of Fruit-trees.</hi> p 2</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Age of Fruit-trees.</hi> ibid.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mans fall, Reſtoring, and Establiſhing.</hi> p. 3</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 2.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sympathy, and Antipathy in Vegetables.</hi> p. 4</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sympathy, and Antipathy of Plants, truly ſtated.</hi> p ib.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Liken<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſs of Natures accord best among men.</hi> p. 6</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>No attaining Communion with God, without a new Nature</hi> ib.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>No cordiall fellowſhip between Regenerate, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenerate perſons.</hi> p. 7.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Perception in Fruit-trees, in fled of ſence.</hi> ib.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Four diſtinct Rankes of Creatures, each Genus including many speties.</hi> p. 8</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>All Creatures are ſubſervient one to another.</hi> p. 9</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 3.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The benefite of due Ordering of Fruit-trees.</hi> p. 16</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55886:15"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>God chaſtneth all his people; ſome more, ſome leſſe, for their profit.</hi> p. 11.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 4.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fruittrees beautiful objects.</hi> p. 13</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Immoderate love to Creatures, dangerous</hi> ibid.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Too much love to Creatures abates love to God.</hi> p. 14</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Communion with Creatures calls for Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God.</hi> p. 15.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 5.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Profits, and Pleaſures, by Fruit-trees.</hi> p. 16</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fruits of Trees, mans Food.</hi> ibid.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Planting Fruit-trees commended by Antient, and late writers.</hi> p. 18</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 6.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Two things, (ſeeming) diſcouragements in Planting.</hi> p. 22.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vaine minds take up with preſent ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> p. 23</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Examples of the greatest perſons in Plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> p. 23</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55886:15"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Many Profits, and Pleaſures in planting Fruit-trees.</hi> p. 27</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 7.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Great Trees in too fat ſoyle, bear not well.</hi> p. 29</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Moderation is best.</hi> p. 29</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A juſt Reprooff of the carnal, careleſs Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie.</hi> p. 30</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Skilfull ordering of Fruit-trees produceth Fruitfulneſſe.</hi> p. 31</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Remove the Cauſe, and the effect ceaſeth.</hi> p 32</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>A due commendation of the Pious, and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Gentry.</hi> ibid.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 8.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The voice of all Creatures to man.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fruit-trees, receive, and looſe their beauty once a year.</hi> p. 35</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The ſtate of all things here below changeable.</hi> p. 36</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fruit-trees are pincht, and endure difficulties in winter.</hi> p. 37</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fruit-trees in the Spring revive.</hi> ibid.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Some Christians go through great tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> p. 38</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55886:16"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The light <hi>of Gods Countenance</hi> refreſheth the ſoul after darkneſse.</hi> p. 41</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 9.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Opinion about deſcention of Sap, exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi> p. 41</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>No deſcention of Sap in Trees.</hi> p. 43</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Spirit, and nature of true Christians, tends upwards.</hi> p. 34</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 10.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fruit-trees are prepared in Nurſeries, to be tranſplanted.</hi> p. 45</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Elder trees transplanted make room for the younger.</hi> p. 46</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Some of the best kinds are to grow still in the Nurſery</hi> p. 47</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nurſeries of Materiall Fruit-trees are apt ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes of Myſtical Fruit-trees in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities.</hi> ibid.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Spirit, and grace of God, is to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before all Natural, and acquired abilities</hi> p. 48</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 11.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Some Fruits ſeem good to the Eye, but are bad to the tast.</hi> p. 50</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55886:16"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fruit-trees improved by ingrafting.</hi> p. 50</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>No works pleaſing to God without ſincerity.</hi> p. 51</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 12.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mulberytrees called <hi>Sapientiſſima Arborum.</hi>
                        </hi> p. 52</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mulberry-trees bud late, becauſe of a tender nature.</hi> ibid.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Some Chriſtians are more valiant for Christ then others.</hi> p. 53</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 13.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fruits ripen ſucceſſively upon the ſame tree; others altogether.</hi> p. 54</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The wiſdom, and bounty of God in the ripening of Fruiis.</hi> p. 55</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 14.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>South-Country trees prosper not in England.</hi> p. 56</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Plant Fruit-trees fitt for the Country.</hi> ibid.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 15.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Redstreake trees formerly of little account.</hi> p. 57</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55886:17"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Redstreake Apples best for Cider.</hi> p. 58</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Comfort after trouble: joy after ſorrow.</hi> ibid.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 16.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>More planting of late years, then formerly</hi> p. 59</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Reaſons for much Planting of Fruit-trees.</hi> p. 60</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cider the most wholſome drink, especially of the bect Fruits.</hi> p. 60</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 17.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fruit-trees ſhew forth the glory of God.</hi> p. 61</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fruit-trees are ingagements to obedience.</hi> p. 62</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>All men act according to their Natures.</hi> p. 63</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fruit-trees change not their Natures.</hi> ibid.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>All mankind have changed their Natures once; and ſome have a double change.</hi> p. 64</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 18.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Heat of the Sun needfull for Fruits.</hi> p. 65</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fruit-trees have a preception of the heate of the Sunn and are refreſhed by it.</hi> ibid.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Believers that walke cloſest with God, bring forth the best fruits.</hi> p. 66</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:55886:17"/>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 19.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Scripture ſaith Fruit-trees were from the beginning, and ſhall be to the End of the world.</hi> p. 67</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The excellencies of all Creatures are united in God, and infinitely more then all.</hi> p. 67</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The Excellencies, and vertues of the Creatures ſhould leade us unto God, and there to reſt.</hi> p. 68</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 20.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Young, ſmall Trees: full of good Fruits.</hi> p. 68</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>God calls ſome of his people in childhood, and youth, others afterwards.</hi> p. 69</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 21.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Groſſe ignorance reproved.</hi> p. 73</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Most people are ignorant both of Gods word, and works.</hi> p. 74</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlearned men may read in the Book of the Creatures.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 22.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>An invitation, and incouragement to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with Fruit-trees.</hi> p. 76</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:55886:18"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Many things in Fruit-trees occaſion admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi> p. 77.</item>
                     <item>1. <hi>Tender Fruits, come forth with covers upon them: the more hardy, without:</hi> p. 77</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 23.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>2. <hi>Different ſubſtances made of one ſubstance.</hi> p 79</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Different Gifts, and Graces wrought by the ſame Spirit.</hi> ibid.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Every gift ought to be improved for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of all.</hi> p. 80</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section 24.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>3. <hi>Grafts and Buds, aſſimilate the Sap of the Stocks.</hi> p. 81</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Section: 25.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>4 <hi>Every ſmall Bud contains the Nature of the whole Tree in it ſelfe.</hi> p. 83</item>
                     <item>5. <hi>The properties of a tree, are in every ſeed.</hi> p. 84</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The ſame flower ſeed brings forth variety</hi> p. 85</item>
                     <item>6. <hi>Many kinds of Fruits upon one tree.</hi> p. 86</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:19"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55886:19"/>
            <head>A DIALOGVE, (OR FAMILIAR DISCOURSE and conference) between the <hi>Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and <hi>Fruittrees;</hi> in his <hi>Nurſeries, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards,</hi> and <hi>Gardens.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Trees speak to Men.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>I have read in Learned and Godly mens workes and the Scriptures alſo declare as much; that yee <hi>Fruittrees can speake, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with men,</hi> (though not with <hi>an arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate distinct voice, and ſound of words, to the outward ſence of hearing,</hi> for that is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per only to <hi>rationall Creatvres</hi>) Yet it is knowne yee can ſpeake very <hi>intelligibly, and convincingly, to the minds, and conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of men,</hi> And can Anſwere their <hi>Queſtions;</hi> and ſpeak many things to their profit and edification; And that yee alwaies ſpeake <hi>the very truth;</hi> and to the <hi>glory, and praiſe of God:</hi> What <hi>Language</hi> is it that yee ſpeake,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55886:20"/> is it <hi>Engliſh,</hi> or <hi>Latin, Greek,</hi> or <hi>Hebrew,</hi> or what other <hi>Language</hi> elſe, wherein yee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with men.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Language of Fruittrees.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>We can ſpeake all <hi>Languages;</hi> We can diſcourſe with any <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or Nation,</hi> in any Language whatſoever; according as people pleaſe to diſcourſe with us, ſo we Anſwer them; every man in his owne Language.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>We in this Countrey, are <hi>Natives of England;</hi> we will therefore ſpeake together in our <hi>Engliſh Tongue,</hi> for that we beſt underſtand; Tell me then firſt of all; <hi>Of what age are yee? of what duration?</hi> (I ſpeake not of theſe individuall Trees here Planted, but of Fruittrees in generall.) <hi>How Long have yee been in the world?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Age of Fruittrees.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ITTREES:</speaker>
                     <p>We are of a very Great Age; even from the beginning of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: which is now (according to common com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation) 5676. yeares or thereabouts: This thou maiſt underſtand by a Token that much concernes the; For we were preſent &amp;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55886:20"/> ſtood by, when thou, and thy wife, did both of you, tranſgreſſe the <hi>Command of our Creator, in the Garden of Eden,</hi> in that yee did eate of the <hi>Forbidden Fruit:</hi> Thou had'ſt liberty enough given thee, which was to <hi>Eate of all our Fruits,</hi> throughout the whole Garden; (Except only <hi>of one Tree,</hi> to try thy Obedience) and that as free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as thou wouldeſt; why then didſt thou breake the command of God; which we never yet did, nor ever ſhall; though we are much inferior to mankind.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Mans fall, Restoring, and Eſtabliſhing.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>Herein yee ſpeake <hi>the truth, and convincingly</hi> indeed; for ſo it was; which we muſt acknowledge to God, and be humbled for it; for it was <hi>a very great tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion,</hi> we loſt our glory, and our Happineſs by it; but bleſſed be God for ever, for <hi>his free Grace,</hi> he hath ſhewed us a meanes, and way of recovery, to our former ſtate of happineſſe, which he did not to the <hi>Angels</hi> that ſinned, but a little while before us; (God never ſpake one kind word to them ſince, nor ever will) O the <hi>justice, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God:</hi> towards them <hi>juſtice:</hi> but to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us <hi>Mercy, and free Grace;</hi> in our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55886:21"/> even all that he hath choſen: Yea, God hath not only <hi>restored, and recovered us</hi> out of our fallen ſtate, but alſo hath ſo confirmed us in it; as that now we can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fall from it any more; as we then did, But this is <hi>a Gloriouſe mistery,</hi> diſcovered to us <hi>in the word of the Goſpell of Chriſt;</hi> wherein yee have no skill, neither can yee ſpeake, as to that matter.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>Section 2.</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Sympathy and Antipathy in Vegetables.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>It hath been aſſerted by Learned men, That there is a <hi>ſympathy, and Antipathy in Plants, Trees, and all Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables;</hi> ſome kinds will not thrive toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which they impute to <hi>Antipathy;</hi> and ſome other kinds flouriſh, and proſper vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorouſly, growing together, which they call <hi>Sympathy:</hi> or a good agreement one with another: What ſay yee of your ſelves, as to this matter.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Sympathy, and Antipathy of Plants duly ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <p>We owne the Notion, if it be but rightly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55886:21"/> underſtood and applyed; for there is ſuch <hi>a contrariety, and heterogeneous quality</hi> in ſome trees, and other Vegetables; as men ſpeake of, And alſo, <hi>a likeneſse, and agreement in Nature,</hi> in ſome others, But it hath been much miſtaken by ſome writers, who have ſaid, That there is an <hi>Antipathy</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene ſome Plants (as the <hi>Vine, and the Colewort</hi>) becauſe they will not thrive to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; but that is not an <hi>Antipathy;</hi> but rather a <hi>Sympathy:</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Lord Baron's Nat: Hiſt: pa: 101. Exp: 480.</note> Becauſe wee <hi>Vines</hi> love the ſame fatt, and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſoyle, as the <hi>Colewort</hi> does; and thence it is that wee turne our Rootes from it, becauſe it hath exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the ſoile and made it barren; But there is a real <hi>Antipathy in Nature,</hi> between ſome trees, which are of Different ſpecies: &amp; therefore they will never thrive together when joyned in Grafting. As the <hi>Apple-tree grafted upon a Peerestock;</hi> and ſo on the contrary; Alſo the <hi>Plum on the Cherry; and the Cherry on the Plum;</hi> They may grow 2. or 3. yeares but will never thrive to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; there is an <hi>Antipathy in Nature,</hi> and they reject each other; And therefore let men in grafting obſerve right ſpecies, and kinds in joyning us together; elſe no profit will accrue to the Husbandman.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:55886:22"/>
                  <head>Likeneſſe of Natures accord best among Men.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>We ſee the ſame thing amongſt men, and Women: There is a very great <hi>Antipathy, and contrariety in their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> one againſt another; an utter enmity in their Natures; Therefore it is neceſſary (in order to Communion, fellowſhip, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of perſons, and ſocieties that they be of <hi>one, or alike Nature?</hi> But the higheſt, and greateſt <hi>Antipathy,</hi> in the world, is that betweene the <hi>Holy Nature of God, and the corrupt nature of Man;</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">No attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, without a New Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> There is no poſſibility of attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Communion and Fellowſhip with God,</hi> or to have any enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, here in this world, or hereafter in the life to come, without a <hi>change of Nature,</hi> The <hi>corrupt Nature of Man,</hi> is quite contrary to the <hi>Holy Nature of God;</hi> Therefore there muſt of neceſſity be <hi>a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing in the spirit of our minds: a new Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> by ingrafting into Chriſt, that ſo there may be apertaking of the <hi>Image</hi> or <hi>Nature of the ſecond Adam, in righteouſneſs and true holineſſe,</hi> as there is of the <hi>first Adam in ſin, and corruption.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:55886:22"/>
                  <head>No fellowſhip betweene Regenerate and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Perſons.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <p>So neither can there be any cordial fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, complacency or delight, betweene <hi>Regenerate, and unregenerate perſons;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of this <hi>Antipathy, and contrariety in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, what fellowſhip hath Christ with Beliall, or he that beleeveth with an infidell:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore perſons in their <hi>Marriage choice,</hi> had beſt conſider, and make ſure of this, in the firſt place: and make other conſiderations ſubſervient, and ſubordinate thereunto.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Quest:</hi> But how is this among <hi>Fruittrees,</hi> ſeeing yee are not <hi>ſenſible Creatures;</hi> but are in a rank, and degree below them.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Perception in Fruittrees instead of ſence.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ITTREES:</speaker>
                     <p>It is true, we are not <hi>ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Creatures;</hi> But yet we are <hi>living Creatures;</hi> And we have a Nature in us ſome what <hi>ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logous to ſence;</hi> we have <hi>Perception,</hi> which is to us inſteed of <hi>ſence,</hi> whereby we know what is <hi>good for us,</hi> and what is <hi>hurtfull to us;</hi> and thereby we <hi>chuſe the one, and reject the other,</hi> in ſome <hi>warme fertile ſoyles</hi> wee thrive much better than wee do in ſome <hi>cold, wett, bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55886:23"/> grounds;</hi> And ſo in reſpect of ſituation, either towards the <hi>Sun, or from it;</hi> in ſhady places.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Four Diſtinct rancks of Creatures each Genus including many ſpecies.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>I perceive then here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, That there is a vaſt difference among the <hi>Viſible Creatures</hi> here upon earth; in their diſtinct and ſpeciſick Natures; w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> may be diſtinguiſhed into foure <hi>ranks, or degrees;</hi> every <hi>Genus,</hi> including divers perticuler, and <hi>distinct ſpecies;</hi> The firſt and loweſt of all are thoſe which are but only <hi>bare, and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſubstances,</hi> without life; as <hi>Earth, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Stones, Mineralls,,</hi> and ſuch like, the ſecond ſort are a degree above theſe, not only <hi>ſubstances,</hi> but they have life alſo; as <hi>Trees, Flowers, Herbs:</hi> and all Vegetables; the third ſort are a degree above them, which have not only <hi>life,</hi> but have alſo <hi>ſence;</hi> as <hi>Beasts, Foules, Fiſhes,</hi> The fourth rank, and degree of Creatures, are above all theſe, which are not only <hi>ſubſtances,</hi> and have <hi>life, and ſence,</hi> but alſo <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as Mankind in all Nations.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:55886:23"/>
                  <head>All Creatures are ſubſervient one to another.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <p>And now as theſe Creatures are thus diſtinct in their degrees, one <hi>Genus</hi> higher then another; ſo by the <hi>Wiſdome, providence, and appointment of God,</hi> they are uſefull, and ſubſervient, one to another, each kind in their diſtinct degrees the <hi>first,</hi> to the <hi>ſecond;</hi> the <hi>ſecond</hi> to the <hi>third,</hi> and the <hi>third</hi> to the <hi>fourth:</hi> The ſimple ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>Earth, water,</hi> &amp;c. feed and nouriſh the <hi>flowers, herbs,</hi> and all <hi>Vegetables,</hi> and theſe nouriſh the <hi>Beasts, Foules, Fiſhes</hi> &amp;c. And theſe feed, and nouriſh the higheſt Rank of viſibles Creatures; all <hi>Mankind,</hi> that ſo he may ſerve, and glorifie God in, and by all theſe.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>Section 3.</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Culture of Fruittrees neceſsary.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>Here are ſome <hi>Fruit-trees,</hi> which I have beſtowed much labour and coſt upon, in ordering of them, by dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about your Rootes, in manuring of them with good ſoyle: and the Branches by Pruning off the one halfe of them (being too
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55886:24"/> cloſe, and too many; And alſo I have cut off the one halfe of your high<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>; for yee were growen and aſpired up, ſo high into the Aire, that the winds and Froſts (in the ſpring time eſpecially) had more power upon you then upon low, ſpread trees; ſo that I hope my labour, hath not beene in vaine: How do yee find your ſelves, do yee perceive your ſelves any whit better, for all this labour, and time beſtowed upon you.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The benefit of due ordering Fruittrees.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>We have a preception<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that we grow more vigorouſly, and ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then we did formerly; for we wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> back bound, before; (a thick hard bark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> incompaſſing us) did very much obſtruct<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and hinder the aſſention of our ſap) which now by thy ordering of us, is looſed; and we receive a more plentiful nouriſhmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> by ſap from the Earth, which feeds all ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> branches; which before cutting aſpired up into the Aire, but now ſpread round in a comly forme, and are full of good fruitts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as thou ſeeſt, And ſo we are every way much the better for all thy labours.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:55886:24"/>
                  <head>God chaſtneth all his People, ſome more, ſome leſse for their Profitt.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>I ſee it is as yee ſay; And as theſe things are to be obſerved for our temporall profitt among fruittrees, ſo alſo they ſerve as a very appoſite <hi>ſimilitude</hi> to ſhaddow out a ſpirituall truth by way of analogie, and reſemblance of Gods dealing with his people, his <hi>Misticall Fruittrees</hi> who, as a moſt wiſe, and carefull Huſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſeeing his Fruittrees beare good fruitts, he Prunes and orders them (ſome perticulars more eſpecially, and that in ſome extraordinary manner) that they may bring forth more fruitts, and better then before.</p>
                     <p>For ſome Chriſtians after that they have attayned ſome good meaſures <hi>of Gifts, and Graces of the Spiritt,</hi> through the want of the <hi>exerciſe and improvement of them, and Christian watchfulneſſe,</hi> they grow negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and Proud and abate of that <hi>vigour of spiritt, zeale and love,</hi> that formerly they had; And therefore the Husbandman takes them in hand, and deales with them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the caſe requireth; He cuts off many of their branches, Ther <hi>exuberant
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55886:25"/> Vaine, carnall imaginations, thoughts, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, intentions, and contrivances</hi>) which riſe up, and extend beyond due bounds, and brings them low, and humbles them greatly; Not only by many afflictions, troubles, and <hi>Diſtreſses of Body, and ſpiritt,</hi> but alſo ſometimes by withdrawing his, ſpirit, and permitting them <hi>to fall into ſome ſinnes;</hi> ſo as to ſhame, and diſhonour them; which workes more effectually for the cure of <hi>Pride and ſelfelove,</hi> then any other meanes can do: St. <hi>Austen</hi> hath a faying to this purpoſe: <hi>I dare affirme it</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that it is profitable for a proud man to fall in to ſome ſcandalous ſin, that by the ſhame of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> he may be humbled:</hi> his meaning is not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that it ſhould be any mans choice to ſin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he may be humbled; but that it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>times Gods way of cure to permitt it as t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſome men.</p>
                     <p>A wiſe <hi>Phyſitian</hi> can ſo temper <hi>poyſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> as to make it (with other ingredients <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>procure, or preſerve health: ſo that in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> theſe things God is ſeene, and to be pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed, and admired, in his diſpenſations to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wards his people; and they to learne obe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dience by the things that they ſuffer, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to be more <hi>thankfull and firutfull,</hi> in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> hearts, and lives afterwards.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:55886:25"/>
               <head>Section 4.</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Fruittrees Beautifull Objects.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>It is a great pleaſure, and delight to walk among you, ſo many beautifull Fruittrees; ſeeing yee grow ſo handſomely, and uniforme; yee grow in order, in ſtraight lynes, every way; (look which way a man will) <hi>decent formes</hi> and order of things are pleaſant to the Eye; as a <hi>Conſort of Muſick</hi> is to the Eare: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides; yee are more beautifull and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome in your various coloured <hi>bloſsomes, leaves, and fruits,</hi> theſe even raviſh the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ences, with their delicate <hi>colours. ſmels, and tasts;</hi> all exceeding gratefull to the ſences; and delightſome to the mind.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Immoderate love to Creatures dangerouſ.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ITTREES:</speaker>
                     <p>We owne what thou ſayeſt to be true; We are indeed fine beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Objects; and deſireable good things, uſefull, and profitable in the lives of men: But thou, and others had beſt take heed, and beware leaſt yee love us too much; that yee ſet not your hearts upon us; for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55886:26"/> 
                        <hi>Lalet anguis in herba,</hi> a ſerpent may be hid even amongſt pleaſant, and beautifull flowers; the old Serpent is ſtill alive; that <hi>bitt, and ſtung thy first Parents;</hi> in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Eden they ſetting their minds too much upon the beauty, and excellency o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Fruits that they ſaw: They ſaw that the Fruits were beautifull to the Eye, and good for food, and they took, and Eate o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> it: being ſeduced alſo by the ſubtilty o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Serpent; And thou maiſt be ſure h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> hath not loſt any of his <hi>Malice, Power, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> Policy;</hi> but is watchfull day, and night<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to do thee; and others miſcheife.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Too much love to Creatures, abates love to God</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>This is a good caution and to be heeded, and obſerved daily<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For the <hi>Pleaſures, and Profitts</hi> of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures do often ſtale away the minds, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> affections even of good men; which abat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> the ſtreame of their love to God: whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> occaſions (more, or leſſe, ſooner, or late<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hastnings, and afflictions,</hi> from the hand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> God; who cannot beare, that the hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of his people ſhould be alienated from hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> by any of his Creatures; Yet neverthele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> here is a lawfull uſe of theſe, and othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:55886:26"/> Creatures, with Pleaſure and delight, ſo it be within due bounds; But this delight in Fruit-trees in Orchards and Gardens (in a kind of Communion, and complacency with them) it ſhaddows out unto us <hi>a great, and ſingular miſtery,</hi> and a priviledge of beleevers; the greateſt on this ſide hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; that is; <hi>Communion, and Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with God, the enjoyment of him for ever.</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Communion with Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures calls for Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God.</note> Sincere, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Chriſtians know by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, what it is to <hi>walke with God; in Fellowſhip with him;</hi> God doth gratiouſly condiſcend to have <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and Fellowſhip</hi> with Man; with ſuch as he hath Choſen to himſelfe, and changed, ſanctified and prepared, as Veſſels of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, for his owne uſe.</p>
                     <p>And herein we need not reſtraine or ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt our love, and affections, as we ought to do towards the Creatures; all we have, or can let out, is too little, and ſmall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>or this infinitely <hi>best Object of Love:</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with, and delight in all other Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ects, muſt be ſubordinate unto this; for all the <hi>good, and deſireableneſſe of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> are but ſo many <hi>Drops derived from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>his infinite Ocean,</hi> in his preſence is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ulneſſe of joy; at his right hand there
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55886:27"/> are pleaſures for ever more.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>Section the 5.</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Many Profitts and pleaſures by Fruittrees.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>There hath been very much ſpoken by Auntient and late writers, about the <hi>Profitts, and Pleaſures</hi> that are found in <hi>Orchards, and Gardens;</hi> And all people (generally) do much commend <hi>The worke of Planting Fruittrees,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>Profitts,</hi> and <hi>Advantages</hi> that yearely do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from <hi>Fruittrees,</hi> Beſides all the delight, and Pleaſures ſuper-added wherein do theſe <hi>Profitts, and Pleaſures</hi> conſiſt, tell us ſome particulars briefely.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Fruits of Trees Mens food.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ITTREES:</speaker>
                     <p>Thou knoweſt <hi>ov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Fruits</hi> are uſefull, and <hi>Profitable</hi> many waie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in the lives of men: They are for <hi>food al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> the yeare long</hi> both for <hi>meate, and drink;</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> was the firſt <hi>Food</hi> given to man; and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in his beſt ſtate, and condition; even i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Paradice, the moſt pleaſant place upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Earth; <hi>our Fruits were his appointe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> food,</hi> he might eate of all our Fruits; (on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:55886:27"/> Tree only excepted:) And <hi>Fruits of Trees</hi> have been <hi>mans food</hi> ever ſince, and ſo ſhall be to the end of the world.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>It is true: <hi>the Fruits of Trees</hi> are good <hi>food,</hi> both for <hi>Man and Beast;</hi> which beeing well ripened, they may be uſed for <hi>wholeſome food</hi> many waies; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially made into <hi>Cider;</hi> the moſt whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome drink known in the <note n="*" place="margin">Vinetum Britannicum by J. W: Gent: p. 18.</note> world; and ſo accounted by Learned, and skilfull <hi>Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> and found ſo to be by <hi>long Experience,</hi> not of particular Perſons only; but by ſeverall Generations ſucceſſively: in ſeverall Countries, where it is temperately, and moderately uſed; as their common drink; which hath been (of late time more eſpecially much <note n="*" place="margin">ſee; Silva &amp; Pomona, by Mr. Euelin. of the Royall Society.</note> celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and commended, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worthy, and eminent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; upon good grounds, both of <hi>Reaſon, and Experience.</hi> As conducing (more then any other Liquors) to <hi>health, and long life;</hi> which are much in eſteem among all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:55886:28"/>
                  <head>Planting of Fruit-trees commended by Antient and late writers.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <p>Now becauſe the <hi>Profitts, and advantages by Planting Fruit-trees</hi> are ſo many, and great, I think it not amiſſe to acquaint my friends here preſent, with the <hi>Praiſes, and Commendations</hi> that ſome <hi>Authors</hi> have given <hi>to this work and imployment of Planting Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees,</hi> that they may be more in love with it, and more diligent in it, for their own Profitt, and for Poſteritie alſo.</p>
                     <q>Varro: <hi>Li.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. de re Ruſtica: hinc profectò Agricolae ad duas metas dirigere debent; ad utilitatem &amp; voluptatem.</q>
                     <q>
                        <note place="margin">Menander.</note> Agricolarum vita voluptatem ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit. Dum triſtia ſpe futurorum ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latur, <hi>est profecto</hi> virtutis &amp; vitae Magiſter Ingenuae omnibus hominibus ager, <note place="margin">Agricultura quid ſit.</note> Mihi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur nihil aliud eſſe Agricultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram quam inſpectâ Plantae Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, &amp; Caeli, &amp; Terrae ei idoneum cultum tribuere, &amp; (ut ita dicam) Caelum cum Terra maritare, vel ſocietatem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirere Caeli, &amp; Terrae ad Arbores.</q>
                     <q>O quam dulciſſimum eſt fructus ex arbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus quas ſeviſti, inſeruiſti, &amp; coluiſti, propriis manibus colligere, &amp; Amicis,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55886:28"/> agnatiſque jactabundus largiri &amp;c.</q>
                     <q>
                        <l>
                           <note place="margin">Virgil in Georg:</note> 
                           <hi>O fortunatos nimium, bona ſi ſua norint.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Agricolas; quibus ipſa procul civilibus Armis,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fundit humo facilem victum juſtiſſima tellus.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                     <q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Aves canoros garrulae funduni ſonos:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Et ſemper Aures cantibus mulcent ſuis.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                     <q>Mira eſt, &amp; in explicabilis horti commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditas: nam ſi neceſſitatem conſidero, agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultura tanto eſt humano generi emolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento; ut eâ carere nullo modo poſſis; ſi utilitatem, inter primas, non poſtrema. Nec quaenam illi poterit comparari: ſi volupta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem dignitati commiſtam, ea eſt excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia &amp;c.</q>
                     <q>
                        <hi>August:</hi> Quid enim hoc opere innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius vacantibus; &amp; quid plenius magnâ con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideratione prudentibus; quid majus mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabiliuſque ſpectaculum eſt, qnam cum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitis ſeminibus, Plantatis ſurculis, tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Arbuſculis, inſitis malleolis, tanquam interrogatur quaeque (vis Radicis &amp; ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis) quid poſſit, quidve non poſſit, unde poſſit, vnde non poſſit; cum rerum natura humana ratio quodammodo loqui poteſt, quid in ea valeat numerorum inviſibilis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriorque potentia; quid extrinſecus adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bita diligentia, &amp; in ipſa conſideratione perſpicere: quia neque qui plantat eſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquid,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55886:29"/> neque qui rigat, ſed Deus qui dat incrementum.</q>
                     <p>Antient Authors define the chiefe part of Husbandry to be this: The Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ought to conſider the Nature of the Trees which he is to Plant, and ſo to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of them as they may have fitt ſoyle, and ſcituation, that they may have the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the Sunne; as much as may be; And there will ariſe great <hi>Profitts, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages:</hi> with <hi>Pleaſure</hi> attending them; O how ſweet (ſaith he) and pleaſant is the Fruit that thou haſt Planted with thine own hand; to eate thereof, and to diſtribute of the ſame to thy Friends, and acquaintance.</p>
                     <p>They ſay the Profitts of Fruit-trees are wonderfull; and cannot be reckned up, there is no end of the Account;</p>
                     <p>St. <hi>Austin</hi> accounts this an excellent im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment; and worthy the eſteem of the beſt men; having many deep miſteries, &amp; ſecrets of Nature, in it, to exerciſe, and imploy the underſtanding of the moſt eminent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; in conſidering the Nature of ſeeds ſown, in Grafting young Twiggs; tranſplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Trees, and many other works about them, to conſider and find out the Nature of theſe things; and to apply our ſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55886:29"/> but in all, to know, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That it is not he that Planteth, nor he that <hi>watereth,</hi> but God that giveth the increaſe.</p>
                     <p>Mr <hi>Boulton</hi> (an eminent, godly Divine in his time) ſaies that <hi>Vinyards, Gardens, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards, and ſuch incloſed Plotts,</hi> are the <hi>Stars, and Paradices</hi> of the Earth.</p>
                     <p>And Sr. <hi>Fran: Ba:</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Eſſayes pa. 226.</note> ſaies; Gardens are the pureſt of humane Pleaſures, the greateſt refreſhments of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of man; without which Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and Pallaces, are but groſſe handi-workes.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>Section 6.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                  <p>Seeing it is manifeſt, and concluded by all men, that this work of <hi>Planting Fruit-trees,</hi> is very <hi>Profitable, and Pleaſant,</hi> how comes it to paſſe, that ſo many men are yet negligent, and ſlothfull in the worke; Many young Gentlemen who have good eſtates in Lands, and might very much improve their Eſtates by Planting; yet are negligent, and all that can be ſaid to encourage them to it will not prevaile to ſet them on worke; what may be the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this groſſe neglect; is their any fault,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55886:30"/> or matter of diſcouragement ariſing from you that doth hinder them.</p>
               </sp>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Too things ſeeming diſcouragements in Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>There are indeed two things (eſpecially) that may perhaps ariſe from us, (ſeemingly) as matters of diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to ſome men; The one is, We cannot bring forth Fruits ſpeedily, to any conſiderable profit; men muſt be content to ſtay, and waite certaine years, ere they can have any great profits from us, And <hi>ſenſuall men</hi> that are all for <hi>preſent Profitts, Pleaſures,</hi> and ſatisfaction of their appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites with preſent things, will not ſtay our time; which is neceſſary for our growth, and increaſe that we may bring forth ſtore of good Fruits; for their Profitt.</p>
                     <p>And likewiſe; The worke, and labour about us ſeems to be but a meane worke, <hi>Young proud Gentlemen</hi> think it a worke, and imployment much below them, to digg in the ground to ſet Trees; they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it too mechanicall, and therefore have a kind of diſdaine of ſuch an imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which too things often hinder ſome men from propagating of us; notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55886:30"/> we are known to be ſo profitable.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Vaine minds take up with preſent ſatisfaction.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>It is true indeed ſome <hi>wild, lightheaded young Gentlemen</hi> that have good Eſtates, runne altogether after the ſatisfaction of their ſenſuall appetites, and deſires, which they may have at preſent, and are impatient of delay; and ſo neglect, and undervalue, theſe profitts by the Planting of Fruit-trees; in regard (as yee have ſaid) there muſt be a time of waiting patiently for Profitts by Planting; but yet the more <hi>wiſe; and ſober Perſons of the Gentry,</hi> who hearken to <hi>Reaſon</hi> more then <hi>Sence;</hi> are conſiderate, and are fully convinced of what hath beene ſaid, concerning the great <hi>Profitts by Planting Fruit-trees,</hi> and other kinds of Trees; and accordingly are very diligent about the worke.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Examples of the greatest perſons in Planting.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <p>But as for that proud conceite of this worke being <hi>below them,</hi> and too <hi>Mechani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call;</hi> let them but conſider what was the worke of the <hi>firſt Man,</hi> and that in his ſtate of <hi>happineſſe.</hi> The worke appointed him by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55886:31"/> God himſelfe, <hi>was to dreſse the Garden and to keep it;</hi> And let them conſider alſo what <hi>Examples</hi> there are recorded of great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who imployd themſelves, with great delight, in <hi>this work of Planting Fruit-trees: Kings, Emperours, and the greatest Powers,</hi> were not aſhamed of it: but performed it with their own hands; <hi>Diocleſian Emperour of Roome,</hi> left his Empire, and betook him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to <hi>this impl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>yment,</hi> in the later part of his life. <hi>Elizeus sportanus</hi> planted ſpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe, and large Orchards; and uſed therein to feaſt, and banquet with his children, and Friend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>: <note place="margin">Ezra 1.2. &amp;c.</note> 
                        <hi>Cyrus King of Perſia,</hi> (who had all the Kingdomes of the Earth given to him) was diligent, and moſt exact in this worke of <hi>Planting Fruit-trees;</hi> with his owne hand; as he himſelfe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged; to Lyſander, when he came to viſit him. See his own words; as they are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded.</p>
                     <q>
                        <note place="margin">Epiſtola alberti Lol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap> ad herculem: Libid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> re Ruſtica: pag. 30.</note> Cyrus minor Perſarum Rex, vir ingenii excelſi, &amp; rerum geſtarum gloria celeberri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, cum ad eum veniſſet Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſander Lacedaemonius, &amp; ipſe ſummis vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutibus p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ſtans, eique dona nonnulla attu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp; ceteris rebus comis, &amp; humanus erga ipſum fuerit; quodam vero die recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ationis,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55886:31"/> cauſſa in quendam hortum magna ipſius induſtria undique conſeptum, &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulari artificio conſitum eum adduxit; Tum Lyſander admiratus egregium omnium re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ordinem, atque proceritates Arborum, illarumque in quincuncem directam ſeriem, &amp; fructuum pulchritudinem, ac odorum, qui e floribus ſpirabant, ſuavitatem, dixiſſe fertur; Atqui Lyſander, meo ingenio iſta ſunt elaborata; mei ſunt ordines, Arboreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que, &amp; Plantae, aliaque quae ita miraris, mea manu ſunt ſara.</q>
                     <q>Tum viciſſim Lyſandrum, ipſius comtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantem purpu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>am, corporiſque eleganti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, &amp; ornatum perſicum auro gemmiſque praetioſiſſimis ſplendentem; reſpondiſſe; O Cyre, quam meri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o beatus ab omnibus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiberis, cum excellenti fortunatua ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ranta conjuncta copulataque ſit indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria.</q>
                     <p>So that ſuch men as are ſo highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited of themſelves, to think this worke, and imployment about Fruit-trees, to be <hi>below them,</hi> are much miſtaken, they need not be aſhamed of it, more then <hi>their bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters;</hi> Neither hath it beene the choice of ſome few Eminent perſons only, but of very many as we find by Records in ſeverall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors; ſee further.</p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:55886:32"/>
                     <q>
                        <note place="margin">Epiſtola alberti Lolii, ad herculem Li: de re Rust:</note> Solemus autem circa Agri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culturae tractationem; duos po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimum fines conſiderare, <hi>uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem nimirum,</hi> quam continuo inde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipere poſſumus, &amp; venuſtate florum, ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatione ſtirpium; proventu fructuum ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere ſolemus. Et in qua ubi<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> magna copia bonarum, &amp; fructuoſarum Arborum ſeſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferat. Nonnullos alios in medium adduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re qui amore rei Ruſticae ita capti fuerunt, ut poſt habitis omnibus dignitatibus, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratibus, Regnis, Victoriis, &amp; triumphis, ad Agriculturam ſe totos applicuerunt.</q>
                     <q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Caelum niteſcere, Arbores frondeſcere,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Vites laetificas pampinis pubeſcere,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ramos Baccarum ubertate incurveſcere,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Segetes largiri fruges, florere omnia.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                     <q>Subſequitur poſtea aeſtas non ſolum flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ut in primis ſunt Lilia, Roſae, Violae hyacinthi, Caryophilli, &amp; infiniti alii orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; ſed etiam frugibus, fructibus, vuis, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malibus, omnibuſque rebus Caeteris ad vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam noſtram neceſſariis ſuſtinendam abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat.</q>
                     <q>Certe ſi recte, &amp; diligenter inquiſiveris videbis profecto omnes ſtudioſos, &amp; litera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tos homines, Ruris ceſeſſu vehementer ſeſ
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55886:32"/> oblectaſſe, illudque ſemper expeciſſe plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimum. Nam praeter aerem liberum, &amp; ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundam viriditatem, quae plurimum ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um excitant, ſpiritus quoque inde recreari, &amp; intelligentiam mirifice acui, certum eſt. O beata, &amp; fincera vita: o ſuave, atque ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtum ocium, &amp; quaſi omni negotio me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius.</q>
                     <q>Agricultura ſola eſt, cui ingenui, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentes viri admoveri debent;
<q>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Quid datur a divis melius mortalibus aegris,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Quam bona, quae pariunt paſſim letiſſima Rura,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Hic hominum primi vitam incoluere beatam,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Cum placidam nondum turbarent praelia pacem,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Cum variis tellus redimitur floribus; &amp; cum</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Arboribus viride redeunt per brachia frondes,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Atque avium dulces cantus nemora avia complent,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Tunc mecum, aut felix nuſquam vitae genus ullum,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Quo ſe mortales factant, aut hoc erit unum.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </q>
                     </q>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Many Profitts and Pleaſures in Planting Fruit-trees.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <p>Thus we ſee what the <hi>Ancient, and more recent writers</hi> (and thoſe of Learning and Eminency in the world) have ſaid, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed of <hi>this worke of Planting Fruit-trees;</hi> both as to <hi>Profitts, and Pleaſures</hi> in the lives of men; and how they have preferred it before other imployments; Therefore there is reaſon all men ſhould have a good
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55886:33"/> eſteeme of <hi>Fruit-trees, and of the works a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them:</hi> eſpecially ſeeing they are profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table not only as to <hi>Temporall Profitts</hi> in the lives of men, from the Cradle to the Grave, from the beginning of the world, to the end of it. But the ſame alſo miniſtring ſo many occaſions, and helps in order to <hi>spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall advantages;</hi> as hath been ſhew'd; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Examples</hi> to us of <hi>Obedience to God,</hi> in that they keep the <hi>Lawes</hi> of their Creator inviolable; after their kinds; in obſerving the <hi>Courſe of Nature;</hi> from the beginning of the world, to the end of it, And conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually ſpeaking to us to do the ſame; Many advantages we have by them; with all <hi>Pleaſures, and Delights</hi> ſuperadded. So that ſuch a worke, carries away the vote, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage of all People, according to the Poet.
<q>
                           <l>Omne tulit punctum, qui miſciuit utile dulci.</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Here are two of the moſt cogent Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that prevaile with all men, <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum ab utili. Et Argumentum a voluptate.</hi> Arguments from <hi>Profitts,</hi> and Arguments from <hi>Pleaſures.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pleaſure</hi> is call'd <hi>ſal &amp; condimentum vitae:</hi> the Salt that ſeaſons all things to us: the <hi>Profitts</hi> are more becauſe of the <hi>Pleaſures,</hi> and the <hi>Pleaſures</hi> are more becauſe of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55886:33"/> 
                        <hi>Profitts.</hi> They being united together do commend, and ſet off each other; more then they would be ſingle, and alone.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>Section 7.</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Great Trees in too fatt ſoyle Beare not well.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>Here are a ſort of Trees that grow in <hi>a very rich ſoyle, deepe, and fatt;</hi> and are faire, handſome, large, lovely Trees, as any I can ſee, but yet they do not anſwer theſe things in their Fruits: I expect they ſhould bring me ſome Fruit, and profit better, and more then other Trees, that grow in <hi>a poore, leane ſoyl,</hi> and are but ſmall Trees to theſe which are growne to a vaſt bigneſſe, and largneſſe of body, and branches: I cannot be ſatisfied with ſuch <hi>poore, and ſmall returnes, from ſuch great Trees,</hi> in ſuch <hi>a rich and fertile ſoyle</hi> as they here grow in.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Moderation is best.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>There is good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we ſhould bring forth good Fruits, and more then thoſe Trees that grow in <hi>poore ground,</hi> but conſider thou whether our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfulneſſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55886:34"/> be not occaſioned by our <hi>too fatt, and Plentifull feeding;</hi> for thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt that <hi>Repletion is an enemy to Generation,</hi> in all Creatures, according to their kinds, <hi>Men and Women</hi> that are too full fed, and grow <hi>groſſe, and fatt,</hi> they ſeldome are <hi>fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full;</hi> as others who are more <hi>moderate, and temperate;</hi> and this is our caſe; by reaſon of our <hi>too full, fatt feeding</hi> in this deepe, and fertile ſoyle, we grow great, and run out yeerely, in <hi>large ſhootes and broad leaves,</hi> but ſhall beare little Fruit while it is ſo with us.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>A juſt Reproofe of the Carnall Careleſs Gentry.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe things are true, and are uſefull in their place, as to tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Profitts, in the ordering of Fruit-trees; But we may learne hence a Leſſon of high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er concernment; it plainly ſhaddowes out unto us, that it is, too manifeſtly ſeene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>ſome great perſons, the Gentry of this Nation;</hi> who being Trees planted (by Gods providence) in a rich, and fertile ſoyle; they grow very great <hi>in power, and dignity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſwelled with high titles of honour, abundance of riches, and the best things the world affords<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> But as for <hi>Fruitfullneſſe</hi> towards God, <hi>spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55886:34"/> Fruits,</hi> they are very few, and ſmall, amongſt many of them, who live <hi>a most carnall, ſenſuall life,</hi> as if there were no life after this; feeding, pampering, and cheriſhing their bodies, while the poore ſoule is neglected, leane, and ſtarven; And ſo ware out a few daies <hi>in promp, and pride;</hi> and in a moment goe downe from the ſtage of the world, into eternall woe, and deſtruction; O miſerable life, that ſome of them live, even whilſt they live <hi>most at eaſe, and in their pleaſures:</hi> Is not he worthy to be accounted a foole, that will chuſe and prefer, <hi>a painted bauble not worth</hi> 2d, <hi>before a rich Treaſure, worth many Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans:</hi> Much more fooliſh are they who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr a ſhort momentany life of ſenſuall pleaſures, before the pleaſures and glory of Eternall life; Conſider this yee that forgett God, leaſt if yee neglect this day of grace, yee ſhortly prove theſe things to be true, by woofull experience, in reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diles Miſeries.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kilfull ordering of Fruittrees produceth Fruitfulneſse:</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>But yet I ſee ſome few of theſe <hi>great Trees,</hi> even in this <hi>rich ſoyle;</hi>
                        <pb n="32" facs="tcp:55886:35"/> who by ſome skill, and extraordinary induſtry of the Husbandman; do bring forth very good- Fruits, and plentifully too; from yeare to yeare; how glad ſhould I be, were yee all ſo Fruitfull; I ſhould then have a greater revenue of Profitts yearely then I have.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Remove the Cauſe and the Effect ceaſeth.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ITTREES:</speaker>
                     <p>Thou knoweſt by Experience, that immoderation and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in any thing is hurtfull, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſe; ſo when thou knoweſt the Cauſe of a miſchiefe, or inconvenience, thou haſt beſt remove it, if thou can'ſt; that ſo the effect alſo may ceaſe; as this <hi>in Nature,</hi> ſo alſo in <hi>Morall,</hi> or <hi>Spirituall things ſublatâ Cauſâ tollitur effectvs.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>This alſo is of high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and further uſe in reference <hi>to the great on's in the world;</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>A due Commendation of the Pious, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Gentrie.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <p>Although <hi>great Revenues, high Titles Dignities, Honours, Riches and Pleaſures</hi> of the world, are great <hi>ſnares, and Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi>
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:55886:35"/> unto thoſe who have them; yet through the mighty, and powerfull opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſpirit of God, in the carefull, and diligent uſe of the meanes of grace, which ſome of the <hi>great Perſons</hi> do exerciſe themſelves in; their minds and hearts are inlightned, and changed from <hi>a ſtate of Nature, to a state of Grace;</hi> who are famous <hi>Examples</hi> unto others in their generations: and have a great influence upon all round about them; being <hi>Patterns of Piety, great Charity, and Vertue;</hi> And ſo are truly <hi>Noble,</hi> as being <hi>Borne from above; Sones and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to the Lord God Almighty.</hi> Though ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording both to <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.26. Not many wiſe men af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh; not many mighty, not many Noble, are called.</note> 
                        <hi>Scripture, Experience, and Obſervation</hi> of inlightned, ſpirituall minds, the greateſt part of ſuch walke in the <hi>broad way,</hi> and enter into the <hi>wide gate</hi> that leadeth to deſtruction, the eyes of their minds being blinded, not only by <hi>Corruption, and Sathan</hi> (as all ſorts by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are,) but alſo dazelled by the glitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſhew, and ſplendor of theſe <hi>Pompous; gaudy, Vanities, Profitts, and Pleaſures, of this world;</hi> and ſo their ſtate is thereby the more dangerous: Then what infinite grace is ſhewed forth <hi>in chuſing, and calling
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55886:36"/> ſome of them;</hi> Notwithſtanding <hi>theſe impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments;</hi> and plucking them as Brands out of the Burning; making them as <hi>rich Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, and Pearles,</hi> among <hi>Pebbles and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſtones,</hi> Theſe perſons then lye under the greateſt <hi>Bonds, and Obligations</hi> that can be to returne anſwerable <hi>Obedience, Duty, and Thankfullneſse unto God,</hi> for his rich<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and free Grace to them <hi>in Jeſus Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> Not only in ſaving them from the wrath to come; but alſo eſtating them in <hi>an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, immortall, inviſible, and that fadet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> not away, reſerved in Heaven for them.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>Section 8.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Omnia f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>orebunt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> proſpiciente Deo.</note> Methinks yee ſwagger, and are very brave, this May-morning; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> your beautifull bloſſomes, and green<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> leaves; whence had yee all this Gallantrie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Voice of all Creatures to Man.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>It pleaſed our boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifull Creator to beſtow it upon us; but i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> is for thee, and for the ſake of mankind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which ingageth thee, and all men to ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>knowledge it; And to ſerve him, and praiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> him with more chearefullneſſe: This is ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Language, and Leſſon to all Men;</hi> which eve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry particuler tree among us, does dail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:55886:36"/> ſpeake aloud: <hi>qui fecit me, propter te, fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit te, propter ſe:</hi> He that made me, for thee, made thee for himſelfe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>But I have ſeene you meanely clothed, ſometimes in the yeare: I perceive yee change your Garments, now and then; have yee ſeverall ſuits of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Fruit-trees, receive, and looſe their beauty once a yeare.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>Yea; we are diverſly clothed we weare out a new ſhuite every yeare; Our bountifull Lord, and Maſter puts upon us a freſh, new Garment every ſpring of the yeare; and we are very beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull to looke upon; all the <hi>spring, and Summer; with various coloured bloſsomes, leaves, and Fruits;</hi> but towards <hi>Autumne</hi> this <hi>brave clothing</hi> looſeth its freſh colour, becauſe <hi>the Sun</hi> (the efficient Cauſe of our Springing, growth, and flouriſhing) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draws from us, and is gone towards the South parts: And as cold weather coms on, theſe our <hi>beautifull Garments</hi> of <hi>Leaves, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nd Fruits,</hi> fade, and fall from us, by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>le, and little, till we are quite Naked; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hen (for a ſeaſon) we are in a melancholy poſture.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:55886:37"/>
                  <head>The state of all things here below changeable.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>Viciſſitude and change, is the ſtate of all viſible Creatures: from <hi>Riches, to Poverty;</hi> from <hi>Poverty, to Riches;</hi> ſometimes <hi>prosperity,</hi> ſometimes <hi>adverſity;</hi> ſometimes <hi>health,</hi> ſometimes <hi>ſickneſſe,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>honour,</hi> ſometimes <hi>diſgrace; good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and evill Report:</hi> turnes and changes of providence; which we ought to be fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for, (that in every ſtate we may be therewith content) by getting <hi>a well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded confidence, and aſsurance of the love of God in Christ;</hi> which never changeth (as all created things do;) but is the ſame for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; without <hi>variableneſse, or ſhaddow of change.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There is evidently, a very great change, and alteration concerning you; betweene <hi>Sommer, and Winter;</hi> (as hath been ſaid) but how is it with you in the <hi>cold, ſharp Winter, in frost, and ſnow, stormes of Haile, Raine, strong, and boisterouſe Wind,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>blasting, killing Winds; and Aires;</hi> have ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> any reliefe or nouriſhment then to feed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> upon; how do yee to live, and hold out i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the time of all theſe difficulties; yee ſhew forth no effects of life, either by <hi>growth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>buds,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55886:37"/> bloſſomes or leaves;</hi> how do yee find your ſelves to be, during <hi>that ſharp time.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Fruit-trees are pincht, and endure difficulties in Winter.</head>
                  <head>Fruit-trees in the ſpring revive.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>It's true indeed: There is a very great alteration in us, betweene Sommer, and Winter; our beauty, and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments being taken from us; and we are left naked, and bare, and ſeem (during all that time) as if we were quite dead; ſo that ſome unskilfull perſons judg us ſo to be indeed; yet we have a conſerving ſap, exiſting in us all that time, which keeps us alive; though we cannot exert it then, becauſe the Sun (which is the efficient Cauſe of our growth) is at that time, farr remote from us: But when it returnes again in the <hi>spring time,</hi> and daily draws neerer to us, then by its warmth and influence, we begin to be a little refreſhed: for though we have not <hi>ſence,</hi> yet we have <hi>perception:</hi> which is to us inſteed of <hi>ſence:</hi> and we ſhew it by the effects; for thou ſeeſt we then begin to plump our buds, which by little, and little do open, and brake forth into Bloſſomes, Leaves, and ſhootes: And by degrees (as
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:55886:38"/> the Sunne draws neerer, and neerer, and it's heare, and influence is ſtronger, and ſtronger upon us, we are more, and more refreſhed by it, our <hi>bloſsome Buds</hi> turn into <hi>Fruits;</hi> and we ſhoote forth uigorouſly, and ſtrongly, and bring forth Fruits, and flouriſh in our beauties all the Summer.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Some Christians go through great tribulations.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe things we find to be ſo according to Nature; And it is a very proper, and appoſite <hi>ſimilitude</hi> of the ſtate and condition of <hi>deſeried ſoules;</hi> all along in Each particular: its one of thoſe <hi>ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes</hi> that runs <hi>equatuor pedibus:</hi> it holds in all reſpects; for ſo it is with Chriſtians: (but more eſpecially with ſome perticular perſons) one time or other in their life; they indure, and undergo <hi>hard, and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult things; great affliction<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, Temptations, and Tribulations,</hi> which befall them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the good pleaſure of God, who or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth, and overruleth all for their good, and profit: thereby purging out <hi>Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and trying their <hi>graces,</hi> to increaſe <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe;</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Pſ: 84.11.</note> for god himſelfe, (who is <hi>a Sunn, and a ſhield</hi> to his people) doth not only withdraw from their ſpiritts
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:55886:38"/> and hides his face, and ſo leaves them in darkneſſe, and they walk in darkneſſe: <hi>Children of Light walk in darkneſſe</hi> (ſome a ſhorter, ſome a longer time;) But alſo he permitts many <hi>outward troubles, afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and croſses</hi> to come upon them upon their <hi>Bodies, Names, Eſtates, Relations: Soule, and Body,</hi> all that concerns them; are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed, overturned, broken, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; as to ſence, and appearance; both to themſelves, and others, that behold them <hi>Job.</hi> 1, 2, 3. &amp;c. And during this long night of darkneſſe; <hi>this hard, and ſharpe Winter ſeaſon,</hi> there is (as it were) <hi>a Death</hi> upon all they have, for he that is the life of the Soule, (as the Soule is of the Body) is gon, their beloved is gone; and hides himſelfe: They ſeek him, but they cannot find him: <hi>Cant.</hi> 3 2. <hi>The Poore, and needy, ſeeke water and there is none:</hi> (<hi>Iſay</hi> 41.17.) and their Tongue faileth for thirſt, they cry after him, but he heareth not, and makes as though he would never heare; nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard them any more.</p>
                     <p>The abſence of <hi>this Sun</hi> makes all (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and without) darke; yea, more bitter then Death it ſelfe: And more then all this, the ſence of the <hi>abſence of God,</hi> and alſo the apprehenſions of the <hi>loſse of God,</hi> the <hi>irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverable
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:55886:39"/> loſſe of God,</hi> is the ſame (in ſome degree) with the <hi>Torments of Hell,</hi> Yea the worſt, and greateſt of the torments of the Damned. <hi>Paena damni;</hi> the paine of loſſe, is agreed by all Divines to be the greateſt tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Hell, worſe then the paine of ſence, that torments the Body (though that be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable too) <note place="margin">Reve. 7.14. Hoſe. 14.7.</note> All theſe <hi>Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and great Tribulations ſome deſerted ſoules</hi> go through and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, <hi>in this ſharp, Winter ſeaſon;</hi> But when <hi>this Sunn</hi> returnes, and draws neere again, the <hi>Fruit-trees</hi> begin to <hi>revive, and spring,</hi> They <hi>revive as the Corne, and grow as the Vine, and ſhoote forth their Rootes as</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon: Then the <hi>Figg-tree putteth forth her greene Figgs, and the Vine with the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Grapes, give a good ſmell:</hi> Cant. 2.13: <hi>When this Sunn of Righteouſneſſe</hi> ariſeth upon the Soule, he refreſheth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoreth comforts to thoſe <hi>distreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed weary Soules;</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Iſay. 57.18.</note> which they are exceeding ſenſible of, and are (as it were) overjoy'd: As marriners at Sea when they are delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from ſome Terrible Tempeſts, and Stormes, from which they were almoſt in diſpaire to have eſcaped; yet with much a do comming ſaffe to Land, how are they
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:55886:39"/> tranſported with joy, and gladneſſe, for their ſafe ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall at their deſired Haven. <note place="margin">The light of Gods Countenance re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſheth the Soule after darkneſſe.</note> This deliverance from theſe ſpirituall ſtormes, and Tempeſts; (in this ſharp, Winter ſeaſon) is much more; Yea, more then can be expreſſed in words; or ſhaddowed out by any <hi>ſimilitude:</hi> it is Joy <hi>unspeakable,</hi> and full of glory: <note place="margin">Heb. 12.11.</note> Then followes <hi>the peaceable Fruits of Righteouſneſſe,</hi> all the reſt of the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of their life: with more <hi>light and Joy,</hi> then if they had never been <hi>in darkneſse;</hi> Even as <hi>Fruit-trees</hi> after <hi>a long, cold ſharpe Winter,</hi> when the warme ſpring comes on, and the heate of Summer followes, all flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in their beauties, and ornaments of <hi>Bloſsomes, Leaves, and Fruits.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>Section 9.</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The opinion about deſcenſion of Sap Examined.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>Some learned men have thought, and aſſerted, that Sap in <hi>Fruit-trees doth deſcend</hi> (in Autumne) from the Branches to the Rootes; <hi>which going down of the Sap,</hi> cauſeth the Leaves and Fruits to fall off, and the Branches to ceaſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:55886:40"/> growing: And Wood-men, and many others, receive it, and hold it (as their common opinion) for an undoubted truth; What ſay yee of your ſelves, as to this matter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ITTREES:</speaker>
                     <p>If Learned men, and others, are of that opinion, they had beſt conſider it againe; and looke better into the grounds of their opinion; <hi>ſecundae cogitationes meliores;</hi> for we deny the thing; Ther's <hi>no going down of any of our Sap:</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is wiſer then ſo, to part with any Sap that it hath gotten: our Sap is our Life; it is our foode upon which we live, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe yearely, and by which we are inabled to bring forth <hi>Bloſſomes, Leaves, and Fruits,</hi> in Sommer yearely; how come we to be of this bulke, and bigneſſe (as thou ſeeſt) but by the <hi>aſsention of Sap,</hi> and the digeſting, and aſſimulating of it; into our ſubſtance, of <hi>Wood, Barke, Leaves, Bloſſomes, and Fruits<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> we ſhould be glad of mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e Sap, if we could get it; but we will part with none <hi>downe againe;</hi> to our Roots; for our <hi>Rootes</hi> are better ſtored with Sap (all the yeare long) then we the <hi>branches.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And beſides this neceſſity of keeping it and impoſſibility of parting with it, the Naturall, and innate property of our Sap is alwaies to <hi>aſcend;</hi> there is an active, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getative
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55886:40"/> ſpirit in us, the Nature of which is alwaies to <hi>aſcend,</hi> and according to the Law of our Nature, can do no otherwiſe; it being a <hi>tenuous, light Body,</hi> or ſubſtance, of a <hi>flammeous, and aerious Nature,</hi> whoſe appetite is alwaies upwards; according to the knowne <hi>Axiome, omne leve ſurſum;</hi> Nay more; ſhould we part with any of our Sap <hi>downe againe,</hi> we ſhould then <hi>fade, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay;</hi> our ſubſtance would be thereby, <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed;</hi> (that as we <hi>increaſe</hi> one part of the yeare by <hi>aſcenſion of Sap,</hi> ſo we ſhould alſo <hi>decreaſe</hi> another part of the yeare, by <hi>deſcenſion of Sap;</hi> and what then would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of us; Therefore there is no ſuch thing in Nature as <hi>deſcenſion of Sap in Trees.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>No deſcenſion of Sap in Fruit-trees.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>I am perſwaded as ye have ſaid; That there is no ſuch thing in Nature, as <hi>deſcenſion of Sap in Fruit-trees,</hi> and have ſeverall Reaſons againſt it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what hath been ſaid: For no <hi>Effect</hi> can be produced without a <hi>Cauſe;</hi> Now there is no <hi>Cauſe</hi> can be (ſo much as colorably) aſſigned, for ſuch an <hi>Effect</hi> in Nature; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we conclude, there is no ſuch thing; for <hi>Sap</hi> when it moves, alwaies <hi>aſcends,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:55886:41"/> 
                        <hi>deſcends;</hi> If any man be yet unſatisfied concerning this, touching the <hi>deſcenſion of Sap in Trees,</hi> (it being deeply radicated in their minds, and an opinion of long ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,) he may receive further ſatisfaction concerning it, from ſix perticular Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt it; grounded upon <hi>Reaſon, and Experience;</hi> ſet forth at large, in a little Booke intituled; <hi>a Treatiſe of Fruit-trees;</hi> by a Practiſer in the <hi>Art of Planting Fruit-trees; pag.</hi> 191. 192. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As for <hi>Leaves of Trees falling in Autumne, and Rootes being better</hi> then (at that time) which ſome at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the <hi>deſcending of Sap</hi>) the <hi>Cauſe</hi> is groſely miſtaked; other <hi>Cauſes</hi> for thoſe <hi>Effects,</hi> are eaſily aſſign'd: Leaves fall off becauſe Sap (at that time) hath done aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending; and Rootes are beſt then, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no ſap aſcends from them, they are then fed; and will firſt be ſerved: The Poet thought it an Excellent thing to find out the true <hi>Cauſes</hi> of things, when he ſaid, <hi>felix qui potuit, rerum cognoſcere Cauſas:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The ſpirit a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans tend upwards.</note> But beſides the Temporall Profitts, and advantages that may ariſe from the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of theſe things; we learne ſome leſſons, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions for ſpirituall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages:
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:55886:41"/> If the <hi>innate spirit, and Sap in Fruit-trees is still aspiring, and aſcending upwards, and never downwards</hi> unleſſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced contrary to its Naturall propenſity, This teacheth us, That ſo it ſhould be with all Chriſtians: Nay; ſo it is with ſuch as are (not nominally only, but) Chriſtians in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; and in truth: Their ſpirituall Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>aspires, and aſcends upwards:</hi> the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature,</hi> (whereof all beleevers are pertakers more, or leſſe) does as Natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>aſcend,</hi> and raiſe, and draw the ſoule (in it's <hi>deſires, affections, and operations</hi>) <hi>upwards Heavenwards, towards Christ, the life strength, and Treaſure of true beleevers; as corrupt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> tends <hi>downwards; Earthwards, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Creatures:</hi> ſo that by this, Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors may try themſelves, and come to know <hi>what Nature, or Principle</hi> dwells, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes in them: <hi>The Tree is knowne hy it's Fruits: Cauſes are knowne by their Effects: ſo alſo in this Caſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>Section 10.</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Fruit-trees prepared in Nurſeries to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>Here is a very large <hi>Nurſery of Fruit-trees;</hi> ſome very <hi>young,</hi>
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:55886:42"/> lately ſping up; ſome of a <hi>middle ſize;</hi> and others very <hi>large faire Trees;</hi> and of all theſe, ſome are <hi>grafted,</hi> and ſome <hi>ungrafted;</hi> Methinks theſe that are of the biggeſt, and eldeſt ſort, (being now prepared and grown large Trees) ſhould be <hi>tranſplanted,</hi> and removed, out of the Nurſery, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where abroad into ſeverall Countries, in Orchards, Gardens, and Fields; that ſo they might have roome to ſpread, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large themſelves, and beare ſtore of good Fruits, for the profit of many.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Elder Trees tranſplanted make roome for the Younger.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s true: Theſe that are faire, large, goodly Trees<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhould be removed from the reſt, of the younger ſort; elſe we that are young, and comming up, are like to be oppreſſed by them, for we ſhall not have roome to grow, and enlarge; And beſides; theſe great, large Trees, will reach, and in tangle one with another, and croſſe, fret, and gall one another; And therefore it is very fit, and neceſſary, that they ſhould be removed hence, for to that end they were planted here: And then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will come up in their roomes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:55886:42"/> as they have donne; and ſo ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively) be removed where they may grow, and enlarge; and be profitable in their Fruits for many yeares.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Some of the beſt kinds, are to grow still in the Nurſery.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>I know that the end of Planting <hi>a Nurſery of Fruit-trees</hi> is to prepare them for <hi>tranſplanting elſewhere;</hi> But yet it is very convenient, and neceſſary too; that ſome of the <hi>best Trees</hi> (ſuch as have the beſt properties in all reſpects) ſhould remaine ſtill in the Nurſery where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to gather <hi>Grafts, and bring forth Fruits,</hi> in order to the preparation of the young, ungrafted Trees, that they alſo may be fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for tranſplantation in due time.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Nurſeries of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall Fruit-trees are apt ſimilitudes of Miſticall Fruit-trees in Vniverſities</note> And this (if it be well con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidered) is a very appoſite <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties of Learning;</hi> being <hi>Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries</hi> of <hi>Miſticall Fruit-trees;</hi> deſigned on purpoſe for inſtruction, and preparation of youth; that they may be <hi>Fruitfull Trees of the Lords Planting, and Grafting;</hi> to bring forth much good Fruit to the Husbandman, that he may be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:55886:43"/> 
                        <hi>Iſay.</hi> 61.3. And to this great end, every one concern'd ſhould labour earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to be fitted, and prepared with <hi>Gifts, and Graces, Learning, and all endowments, and qualifications of the Mind:</hi> And having received <hi>Talents,</hi> then to improve, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy them, for their Maſters uſe, that ſo they may receive a reward. It is neceſſary (as was ſaid) there ſhould ſome of the <hi>chiefe, and Principall Fruit-trees,</hi> remaine in the <hi>Nurſery</hi> for <hi>Governors and Tutors,</hi> in every ſociety, to prepare the younger ſort for tranſplantation, into ſeverall parts for publique imployment, in the <hi>Church, and Common-wealth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The ſpirit, and Grace of God, is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, before all Naturall, and acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red abilities.</note> Now the <hi>maine, and chiefe thing</hi> to be laboured for, and moſt neceſſary to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned, is <hi>the Spirit, and Grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>f God; humane Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and Naturall parts, and Abilities;</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by Study, and induſtrie, are of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler uſe, and advantage; and all indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors are diligently to be uſed for attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof; but theſe alone, are to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſhort to ayme at, or attaine the <hi>highest end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> the <hi>glory of God;</hi> For Man <hi>by Nature,</hi> ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> have no higher <hi>End</hi> then <hi>himſelfe: his ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> intrests:</hi> As <hi>water,</hi> in its current, can riſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:55886:43"/> no higher (of it ſelfe) then the <hi>spring head:</hi> every thing acts according to its Nature, and can do no otherwiſe; Therefore <hi>a Principle of grace</hi> is abſolutely neceſſary, This is (ſpiritually) <hi>the Philoſophers Stone,</hi> that turnes all Naturall attainments<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> into Gold; it uſes, and improves all <hi>to spirituall Ends, and uſes:</hi> in order to the <hi>glory of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> ſo that we muſt get <hi>this,</hi> or we get <note n="*" place="margin">Si Chriſtum diſcis, ſatis est, ſi caetera neſcis. Si Chriſtum neſcis nihil eſt, ſi caete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra diſcis.</note> nothing: Every one ſhould be of ſuch a ſpirit as <hi>Luther,</hi> who prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted Earneſtly that God ſhould not put him off with <hi>worldly things, or Naturall Gifts,</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we ſhould be earneſt with God, and take no nay; no denyall; Though we ſhould aske <hi>temporall things conditional<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi> (if it be the will of God to give them) yet we may, and ought, to aske <hi>spirituall things</hi> (which are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>olutely neceſſary) without condition: <hi>The Kingd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>me of heauen ſuffereth violence, and the violent take it by force: Mat.</hi> 11.12.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:55886:44"/>
               <head>Section 11.</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Some Fruits ſeeme good to the Eye; but are bad to the Tast.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>I obſerve many Trees in this Garden, which are faire large Trees to looke upon; they flouriſh yearely with <hi>broad greene Leaves, and beautifull bloſſomes,</hi> and ſpring up with <hi>large ſhootes;</hi> but they bring forth <hi>no good Fruits:</hi> ſome Fruits they bring forth, which are large in bulk, and ſubſtance, and have <hi>a faire, and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full colour,</hi> but their <hi>taſt, and reliſh is nought;</hi> the Husbandman likes not their <hi>Taſt;</hi> they are of a <hi>ſower, ſharpe, bitter reliſh:</hi> very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant: If yee bring forth no better Fruit hereafter, yee ſhall be cut down and mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> fuell for the fire: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſhould yee cumbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the ground.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Fruit-trees improved by ingrafting.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>We grow in a goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> and freſh ſoyle, and are large in bulk, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſubſtance, as other Trees, and we bea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Fruits according to our Natures; but w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> were never ingrafted, as ſome other Tree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="51" facs="tcp:55886:44"/> are, which grow by us; ſo that we growing ſtill upon our own <hi>naturall, wild stocke,</hi> and Roote, we bring forth Fruit accordingly. And ſo are like to do, untill we have an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration <hi>by ingrafting.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>No workes pleaſing to God without ſincerity.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>Herein yee beare the likeneſſe, and reſemblance of <hi>hypocrites</hi> in the <hi>Viſible Church;</hi> who live amongſt true beleevers; and make a faire ſhew, with an <hi>outward forme,</hi> and Profeſſion of Religion, in all <hi>externall Duties;</hi> but becauſe they are not <hi>ſincere, and upright,</hi> have not the <hi>truth of grace,</hi> nor were ever really ingrafted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, but grow ſtill upon the <hi>old stocke of corrupt Nature;</hi> thence it is, that their <hi>Fruits</hi> are <hi>nought, and unpleaſant to God,</hi> the Husbandman; tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gh they are never ſo faire, and beautifull on the outſide, yet wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>a good Tast;</hi> that is they have no good <hi>Ends</hi> in any thing they do; they make not the <hi>glory of God</hi> the chiefe, and maine <hi>End</hi> of that they do; for all men by Nature make <hi>themſelves</hi> their <hi>End;</hi> and not the <hi>glory of God;</hi> and therefore they are not accepted of God: ſuch had need to conſider their ſtate (whilſt it is called to day) and ſee that they
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:55886:45"/> reſt not on this ſide <hi>an intereſt in Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>Section 12.</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Mulberry-trees called Sapientiſſima Arborum.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>Here are a certaine Number of <hi>Mulberri-trees</hi> in a row by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; which are a kind of Trees in great eſteeme among men: in ſeverall reſpects: your Leaves are the beſt foode for <hi>Silke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wormes;</hi> And your Fruits are exceeding good to make <hi>Syrups,</hi> for divers uſes which Apothecaries, and others do make yearely; And yee are called by ſome auncient Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors (who write of Fruit-trees) <hi>Sapientiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima Arborum;</hi> How come yee to be <hi>wiſer</hi> then other Trees; How are any Trees ſaid to be <hi>wiſe,</hi> what ſay yee of your ſelves.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>We owne no ſuch <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pithite as wiſe:</hi> we are no <hi>wiſer</hi> then other Trees; but ſome men are pleaſed ſo to ſay of us, becauſe we keepe in, and ſhew not our Buds, nor ſpring till late in the yeare; about the beginning of <hi>May;</hi> when all the cold froſty weather is gone, and paſt; But this is according to the courſe of Nature, (the Law of our Creation) which we, and all other Trees do conſtantly obſerve; And
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:55886:45"/> in this is ſeehe the <hi>wiſdome of our Creator,</hi> (who doth all things wiſely) and hath made us ſo to do; <note place="margin">Mulberry-trees bud late, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Nature.</note> For we are of a more <hi>weake, and tender Nature,</hi> then many other <hi>Fruit-trees</hi> are; which bud, and ſpring (it may be) 6 weeks, or two Months before us; as <hi>Cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytrees, Plumtrees,</hi> and other Trees do; But if we ſhould dare to peepe out, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare ſo ſoone, we ſhould not be able to beare it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>It is very certaine that there are diverſities of Natures and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties among Fruit-trees (as all other Creatures) and therefore they muſt be planted, and ordered accordingly; ſome are ſo tender that they will not thrive; nor beare Fruits, but <hi>against a wall,</hi> and that upon the <hi>South-Sun too;</hi> and carefully, and tenderly ordered: others will grow, and beare well in <hi>the open Fields;</hi> notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all <hi>cold, froſts, storms, and winds,</hi> that they meete with.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">ſome Chriſtians are more valiant for Christ, then others.</note> But this may be transferred to a higher uſe; And gives us to underſtand; That this is even ſo among <hi>ſpirituall Fruit-trees; Profeſſing Christians;</hi> ſome are more hardy Souldiers, and more valiant
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:55886:46"/> then others; And can ſtand out againſt, and encounter with, more, and greater dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, then others; (though true belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers) can do: ſome have a great and ſtrong faith: <note place="margin">Mat. 15.28.</note> 
                        <hi>O Woman great is thy faith:</hi> others have but <hi>a weake faith, O yee of little faith; Mat.</hi> 6 30. Some have great meaſures of the Spirit of God, light, wiſdome, and knowledge; others are but <hi>Babes, and Children</hi> in underſtanding, and grace; ſome Chriſtians have <hi>much love to Christ, and zeale for him;</hi> (as having the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtations of his love more cleare, and evident to them, then ſome others have) ſome others <hi>Love but little,</hi> and all is <hi>weake in them,</hi> and ſo they can <hi>do but little, nor ſuffer for Christ;</hi> the moving <hi>Cauſe</hi> being but weake in them, the <hi>Effects</hi> are Anſwerable.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>Section 13.</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Fruits ripen ſucceſſively upon the ſame Tree; others altogether.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>I obſerve That ſome kinds of theſe Fruit-trees do bring forth their ripe fruits <hi>gradually, and ſucceſſively;</hi> upon the ſame Tree, ſome of the Fruits are ripe, and ready to be gathered ſeverall
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:55886:46"/> weekes before the reſt; as amongſt <hi>Apre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cotts, Peaches, Cherrys, and Plums,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>Sommer Fruits;</hi> we find ſome Fruits <hi>ripe,</hi> whilſt others on the ſame Tree, and ſame Bough, are yet <hi>hard, and greene:</hi> But ſome other kinds of Trees bring forth their Fruits <hi>ripe, and ready together</hi> all at one time, upon the ſame Tree; as <hi>Pippins, Peremains,</hi> and all <hi>Winter Fruits;</hi> What is the Reaſon of this variation in the ripening of the Fruits of Trees.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Wiſdome and bounty of God in ripening of Fruits.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ITTREES:</speaker>
                     <p>Thou maiſt herein ſee, and obſerve the <hi>Wiſdome, bounty, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our Creator;</hi> For if we that are <hi>Cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytrees<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Plumtrees,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>ſommer Fruits,</hi> ſhould bring forth our Fruits <hi>all at once,</hi> there would be <hi>a glutt,</hi> of Fruits; And we ſhould do more hurt, then good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt People; for we are no laſting Fruits; we cannot keepe (as thou knoweſt;) but ſhould in a few daies rott upon thy hand; Therefore God gives our Fruits to thee <hi>ſucceſſively;</hi> ſome one day, and ſome ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as thou, and others may make uſe of them; for <hi>health, and Profitt;</hi> And as for
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:55886:47"/> 
                        <hi>hard, Winter Fruits,</hi> they are ripe all of them together on the ſame Trees, that ſo they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> gathered altogether, and laid up in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ore, for uſe all the yeare long; And is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> not the like <hi>Wiſdome, bounty, and goodneſse,</hi> from God ſhewed to all people in this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as in the former<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though each of them in different <hi>respects, as hath been</hi> ſaid.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>Section 14.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                  <p>Here are a ſort of Trees that do not thrive, nor proſper, as other Trees do; what's the reaſon? ſeeing yee are as well planted, and preſerved, as other Trees which grow neere unto you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">South Country trees, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>per not in England.</note> We are <hi>forreners;</hi> this is not our <hi>Native Country</hi> we were brought from beyond the Seas, from a warme Clymate; where we had a <hi>strong heate,</hi> and influence of the Sun; but we are here in <hi>a cold Country,</hi> and it agrees not with us, we ſhall never grow, nor proſper, nor bring forth Fruits to pleaſe thee, or for thy Profit.</p>
               </sp>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Plant Fruit-trees fitt for the Countrey.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>I beleeve what ye ſay
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:55886:47"/> to be true; Many Gentlemen of great eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, to pleaſe their minds, have ſent for, and bought many rare Plants, and Trees, from <hi>forraine parts,</hi> out of the <hi>South-Countries,</hi> of <hi>France, Spaine, Italie,</hi> and other Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne Clymates and planted them here in England, ſeverall degrees <hi>Northward;</hi> which though it will beare many kinds of good fruits to perfection, and ripeneſſe (ſuch as are fitt for the Countries) yet it will not beare good <hi>Orringes, Lemons, Pomegrana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> and ſuch like Fruits of the South Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; Therefore they had better beſtow their coſt, and paines about Fruit-trees that are knowne by long Experience to be profitable unto <hi>all that plant</hi> them.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>Section 15.</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Redstraketrees formerly of little Account.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>Here are <hi>Redstrake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees</hi> full of lovely apples: are theſe the true <hi>Redſtrakes</hi> that makes the rare <hi>Cider</hi> in <hi>Herefordſhire,</hi> ſo much in eſteeme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all men, How come they to be ſo much in requeſt now; its not long ſince they went by the name of <hi>Skidmores Crabs;</hi> was not that a diſparagement to the Trees, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:55886:48"/> Fruits; how come they now to be in ſo much requeſt and eſteeme every where.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Redſtrake apples best for Cider.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>It's true; we grew, and bore Fruits for many yeares; and our Fruits were called <hi>Skidmores Crabs,</hi> and were very much undervalued; and in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement for many yeares; but when our Natures were conſidered, and tryed; and men had Experience of us, our Fruitt was found to be better then any other ſort of Fruit for <hi>Cider;</hi> and now we are every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where cryed up, and in great eſteeme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all men.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Comfort after trouble Joy after ſorrow.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>I am very glad to heare it: for the knowledge hereof is Profitable many waies; the conſideration of this may be of an higher uſe, and ſhaddowes out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, a truth evident to Experience, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> ſo it often happens to the people of God through his providence for their good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> They may, and often fall under diſgrace and reproch among many becauſe of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Sin, temptations, and afflictions,</hi> that God, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:55886:48"/> good Ends, permitts them to fall into; but yet upon their returne, and reſtoring, God in his own good time, brings them out of all their <hi>troubles; and diſparagements;</hi> and makes them in eſteeme more then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; which fell not as they did: The <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall</hi> is an inſtance herein; For when their <hi>Natures, and Fruits</hi> are knowne, and made manifeſt, he will get them <hi>praiſe, and fame, in every place, where they have beene put to ſhame. Zeph.</hi> 3.19.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>Section 16.</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>More Planting of late yeares, then formerly.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>It is obſerved by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny people, that there hath been <hi>much Planting of Fruit-trees of late yeares,</hi> more then formerly; Men have Planted more Fruit-trees within 30 or 40. yeares laſt paſt, then in ſeverall hundreds of yeares in former ages; as is manifeſt by Orchards that are planted: What is the reaſon that Fruit-trees are ſo much in eſteeme now, and of late time, more than in former times.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:55886:49"/>
                  <head>Reaſons for much Planting of Fruit-trees</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ITTREES:</speaker>
                     <p>The Reaſon is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident; Becauſe men of late time have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and made ſearch into the Nature of our Fruits: And have found out the particuler <hi>Profitts, and advantages that come by us,</hi> in many reſpects; not only as to the <hi>ſale <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>f the Fruits</hi> to thoſe that buy them; but alſo as to <hi>pleaſant, and wholeſome Foode,</hi> all the yeare long in the family; And particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly for <hi>Cider,</hi> which is of late time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded generally, to be the <hi>moſt wholeſome liquor in the world;</hi> being found ſo to be <hi>by Experience:</hi> Not only preventing diſeaſes, which other drinks do breed in the Body; but alſo cures many already contracted: And therefore no marvell Fruit-trees are in eſteeme now, more then formerly.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Cider; the moſt wholſome drink: eſpecially of the best fruits.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SB:</speaker>
                     <p>It is undoubtedly true; That <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> in generall, is the <hi>most wholſome drink,</hi> in refference both to <hi>health, and Long life;</hi> though made of ordinary, and common Fruits. But there are <hi>certaine peculiar
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:55886:49"/> Fruits</hi> (now or late time,) found out, and known, which make<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Cider</hi> far beyond, (and better, then) the <hi>common Cider:</hi> As the <hi>Redstrake, the double Red-redstrake; Gennet Moyles;</hi> and ſome other kinds that might be named: And ſo long as <hi>health and long life</hi> is in eſteeme with men, ſo long will <hi>Cider</hi> be in eſteeme alſo; as the cheif meanes to attaine <hi>theſe Ends;</hi> Learned, and judicious <hi>Phyſitians</hi> do alſo concurre therein, and commend <hi>ſyrupum de Pomis; vinum Pomaceum; vinum Britanicum</hi> &amp;c: ſee <hi>London diſpenſatory;</hi> compoſed by a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Phyſitians pa:</hi> 38: And a famous <hi>Phyſitian</hi> in his time gives it this commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation: <note place="margin">Julius Palma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Lib: de Morois: p. 248.</note> 
                        <hi>Pomaceum è ſucco Malorum dulci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, quae maturitatem conſequta ſunt; ſatis de fae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>atum, matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, tenue, Subflavum, melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholicis adeo ſalubre eſt; &amp; omne potionis ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus bonitate vincat.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>Section: 17.</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Fruit-trees ſhew forth the glory of God.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>I unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtand that yee <hi>Fruit-trees</hi> are Creatures that God hath made to manifeſt, and ſhew forth his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:55886:50"/> And that yee do it continually, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of your Creation, The <hi>wiſdome, Power, goodneſse, bounty, care, and love of God,</hi> towards man, is ſeen, and clearely manifeſt in you; evident to the Reaſon, and underſtanding of men: And therefore yee are worthy to be eſteemed, and commended; and to be ſet before us as Examples, and incentives to the like Obedience: And there is reaſon we ſhould exceed you in ſetting forth the glory of God, as much as we do in our <hi>Natures,</hi> we being created <hi>a higher rank of Creatures</hi> then yee; and for whoſe ſake, &amp; uſe, yee were created.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Fruit-trees are ingagements to Obedience.</note> Thou haſt ſaid the truth: and therefore ſee thou do, and performe accordingly: And that in a due proportion too; anſwerable to thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, as to thy created Nature above us; elſe we ſhall (one day,) be witneſſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, for god, our Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, as ſure as we are now <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, Motives, and Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> to thee, of obedience to God; ſee that thou make <hi>the glory of God,</hi> the cheif End of thy life; in all the actions of thy life, as we do.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:55886:50"/>
                  <head>All men act according to their Natures.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>This is indeed, the End of mans Creation; but men general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by reaſon of the corruption of Nature in all mankind do make <hi>themſelves the End</hi> of their living in the world: and all their thoughts words, motions and waies, in the world, is for <hi>ſelfe;</hi> that Idoll ſelfe is ſet up, and worſhiped, by every man, and woman Naturally; untill God worke another <hi>Nature, and Principle;</hi> even a <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, and spirituall Nature; his own Nature:</hi> And then we do as naturally worke and act for the <hi>glory of God,</hi> and his intereſts in the world, as before we did for <hi>our ſelves.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Fruit-trees change not their Natures.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou telleſt us now of a Miſtery, we perceive not any ſuch thing in our ſelves; as a change in our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; what meaneſt thou by a <hi>change of Nature;</hi> we never changed our Natures, from the beginning of the world to this day; but have kept, and obſerved the Lawes of our Creation, without the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:55886:51"/> leaſt violation; and ſo we ſhall do to the end of the World.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>All mankind have changed their Natures once and ſome have a double change.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>Its true; yee never <hi>changed your Natures,</hi> wherein yee were firſt created; but all mankind have <hi>changed their Natures;</hi> and the natures of ſome have beene <hi>twice changed;</hi> ſince their firſt Creation: firſt in <hi>Paradice,</hi> even whilſt yee ſtood by, and were <hi>witneſſes, of that ſad change;</hi> from <hi>a state of holineſſe to a state of ſin, and Corruption</hi> by that act of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in eating the forbidden Fruit, of one of the Trees in the ſame Garden, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in yee were planted; but the ſecond change of our Nature, yee know nothing of; this is from that woefull ſtate of <hi>corruption, and ſin,</hi> to the ſtate of <hi>grace, and Holineſſe;</hi> This ſecond change of our Nature is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar only to, ſome particular perſons who are called, and ſanctified in due time (in their generations;) and at laſt Eternally ſaved;</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:55886:51"/>
               <head>Section 18.</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Heate of the Sun needfull for Fruits.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe Trees that grow moſt in the Sun, I ſee beare the beſt Fruits; thoſe that grow much in the ſhade and have little Sunn, their Fruits are not halfe ſo good as the other, what ſay yee, is the Cauſe of ſuch difference in the Fruits.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Fruit-trees have a preception of the heate of the Sunn and are refreſhed by it.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>The <hi>Cauſe</hi> is plaine, and evident: We that grow in the Sun are exceedingly refreſhed by it's heate, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, it is the efficient Cauſe of our life, and growth: For in the ſpring of the yeare we have a preception of its drawing nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and neerer, every day towards us, which we are very glad of; and expreſſe the ſame in our budding, bloſſoming, and Fruitfulneſſe; And our Fruits are alſo better ripened, and concocted by the heate of the Sun then thoſe are which grow in the ſhade.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:55886:52"/>
                  <head>Beleevers that walke cloſest with God, bring forth the beſt Fruits.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>This is plainly ſo; And it is true alſo in us; we that are Chriſtians, and walke in the light of Gods Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, ſuch have the refreſhing influence thereof, God is <hi>a Sun and ſhield</hi> to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: <hi>Pſ:</hi> 84.11. And the <hi>neerer, and cloſer</hi> any beleevers walke with him, the more fruitfull they are; And the more ſweet are all their Fruits.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>Section 19.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                  <p>Here are multitudes of goodly Fruit-trees, And wee Experience that yee do yearely bring forth ſtore of beautifull, and wholeſome Fruits; for our profitt; how long are yee to continue with us, in your <hi>beauties, vertues, and profitts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES.</speaker>
                  <p>As we were from the Creation of the world; and ſerved the <hi>first man;</hi> ſo ſhall we continue to the end of the world; for the uſe, and ſervice of the <hi>last man,</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:55886:52"/>
                  <head>The Scripture ſaith Fruit trees were from the beginning; and ſhall be to the End of the world.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>I remember it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: God having created Adam, he put him into the Garden; after he had cauſed eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Tree, bringing Fruit after his kind to ſpring up out of the Earth, he gave the Fruit to Adam for food; And the Scripture alſo tells us, men ſhall be planting Fruit-trees, when Chriſt comes to Judgment: <hi>As is was in the daies of Noah: they Planted they Builded: Even ſo ſhall it be in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the Sonne of Man:</hi> Luke. 17.28.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAM:</speaker>
                     <p>But whence are all your vertues; your good, and uſefull Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties in the lives of Men; What is the <hi>Primum mobile,</hi> the originall, and firſt Cauſe, of all excellencies, in you.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The excellencies of all Creatures are united in God: and infinitely more then all:</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe were given us by our wiſe and bountifull Lord, and Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, who as he made all his Creatures, ſo alſo he gave to every individuall, their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:55886:53"/> diſtinct ſpecificall properties, and Natures, as it pleaſed him.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The good, and vertues of the Creatures ſhould leade us unto God, and there to reſt.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>It is manifeſt then hereby that he is the <hi>Originall and fountaine of all the good things in the world,</hi> in and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the Creatures, in the <hi>Heavens, Earth, and waters;</hi> and all the <hi>Excellencies,</hi> and <hi>rare properties,</hi> of <hi>Beauty, ſweeteneſſe, and goodneſse</hi> in any reſpect whatſoever, that is in any, or in all the Creatures, they are <hi>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited in God the chiefe good:</hi> And with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finiteneſſe above them all: And therefore from the ſight of you, his Creatures, and in our deſiring, and uſing of you, with your <hi>vertues, and properties,</hi> we ſhould be drawn to God, and deſire, and chuſe him above a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>or all his Creatures,</hi> as being the cheife good.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>Section 20.</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Young, ſmall Trees: full of good Fruits.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>Here are a number of <hi>Young, ſmall Trees</hi> that I ſee are full of <hi>faire beautifull, and lovely Fruits;</hi> which is a very
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:55886:53"/> rare ſight to behold, though they are not above 3 or 4 yeares old, from their engraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, yet they beare more Fruits then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers here (not farr from them,) that are three or fourſcore yeares old, what is the reaſon hereof.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>We were all of us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted whilſt we were but <hi>young, and ſmall Trees,</hi> with choice, and ſpeciall Grafts, and therefore it is naturall to us to beare good Fruits early.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>That is indeed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the will, and pleaſure of the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, if it ſeeme good unto him to graft ſome <hi>whilst young,</hi> others when grown up to a <hi>stronger body,</hi> and to let others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone without grafting; who ſhall find fault with him, for uſing this his freedome, and liberty. And it is alſo manifeſt that it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo amongſt Chriſtians: ſo God dealeth with them: <note place="margin">God calls ſome of his people, in childhood, and youth: others afterwards.</note> ſome he calls, and converts <hi>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi> even in their <hi>childhood, and youth,</hi> others in their <hi>middle age;</hi> ſome he calls the <hi>first houre of the day;</hi> ſome the <hi>Eleventh:</hi> and ſome the <hi>last houre, in elder age:</hi> But they who come to God <hi>in Childhood, and youth,</hi> have great, and many ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of thoſe who come afterwards. It
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:55886:54"/> is Gods command that we ſhould come to him, early, betime and ſoone as may be in Childhood, and youth: <note place="margin">
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dum &amp; molle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutum es; nunc, nunc properundus &amp; acri; fiagendus ſine fine ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a Perſ: ſat. 3.</note> 
                        <hi>Eccl:</hi> 12.1. <hi>Remember now thy Creator in the daies of thy youth, while the evil daies come not;</hi> ſuch as chuſe rather to ſerve the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, and their owne luſts, in <hi>Childhood, and youth,</hi> and think to come to God after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <hi>in old age;</hi> let them hearken to what God hath ſaid concerning ſuch, <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.24. <hi>Becauſe I have called, and yee refuſed; I have stretched out my Hand, and no man regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, &amp;c. I will laugh at your calamity, and mock when your feare commeth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But ſuch as begin to follow God betimes, early, <hi>in their childhood and youth,</hi> and to bring ſorth good Fruit whilſt they are <hi>young and of tender yeares,</hi> and give unto God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> their <hi>ſpring time,</hi> their <hi>virgin yeares,</hi> they uſually know more of the <hi>mind of God,</hi> and of the <hi>love of God,</hi> then others: And have greater evidences, and manifeſtations of the love, and favour of God then others have; they are uſually, <hi>ſpeciall, and remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able perſons,</hi> above others; and receive more favours from God then others of his people do, who come not in to God ſo ſoone: We ſee inſtances of this in Scripture:
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:55886:54"/> in <hi>Samuel the Prophet:</hi> who was called <hi>of a child:</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. ſo the <hi>Prophet Jer: Ch</hi> 1.6. who was ſanctified <hi>from the wombe: Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph:</hi> who (for bringing forth good Fruit, when he was <hi>but</hi> 17. <hi>yeares of age</hi>) was ſold into Egipt by his brethren: what remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able favours did he receive from God, all his daies. <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.2. <hi>Obadiah,</hi> feared God <hi>from his youth:</hi> 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 18.12. a ſingular perſon in his time. The <hi>Prophet Daniell:</hi> began to feare God <hi>in his youth Dan.</hi> 1. And God ſhewed him miracles of his care, and Love: he had Learning, and wiſdome, in all Viſions, and dreames <hi>Dan.</hi> 1 17. beſides the immediate comforts of the ſpirit of God, an Angell was ſent with a ſpetiall meſſage to him, to tell him he was greatly belov'd of God, And God wrought a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle in preſerving him from the Lyons: The <hi>Prophet David,</hi> of a <hi>Young Twigg</hi> was ingrafted into Chriſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 71.5. Taught of God from <hi>his youth ver.</hi> 17. And who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had a greater teſtimony from God, then he: <hi>a Man after Gods own Heart.</hi> And who ever had clearer evidences of the love of God; (and conſequently communion with God) than he.</p>
                     <p>How great a Prophet was <hi>John the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> who was filled with the Holy Ghoſt,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:55886:55"/> and ſanctified in the wombe: <hi>Luke.</hi> 1.15. The <hi>Apostle John,</hi> (called the beloved diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple,) began to follow Chriſt <hi>in his youth,</hi> and had intimations of Chriſts love, more then the reſt of the Diſciples; he leaned on his breſt, and lay in his boſome: he had full aſſurance of the love of God to him: 1 <hi>Jo:</hi> 4.13.14. and <hi>Ch:</hi> 5.19.20. 1. <hi>Jo:</hi> 3.14.24. <hi>We know we are of God: We know we are in him: We know we are tranſlated from Death to Life &amp;c.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all this: ſuch as are Engrafted into Chriſt whilſt they are <hi>young, and tender twiggs,</hi> they attaine unto <hi>large growths, and meaſures of grace;</hi> If one have but a ſmall meaſure of grace, (but as a graine of Murſterdſeed) if he begin with it betime, in his <hi>childhood, and youth;</hi> it will improve, and grow, in many yeares, to a large mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and degree: their <hi>Brooke will become a River, and their River will become a Sea:</hi> Every <hi>Act of Grace,</hi> will add to the <hi>habite of grace:</hi> They ſhall proceede from <hi>strength, to ſtrength, from Glory, to Glory, by the Spiritt of the Lord:</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>Section 21.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                  <p>Yee have many Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:55886:55"/> frequently; have you this familiar diſcourſe with every one, as we have at preſent, and as often as we are diſpoſed.</p>
               </sp>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Groſſe ignorance reproved.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>Many people (of all ſorts) come from time, to time, and walk among us, and look upon us, and commend us, for brave handſome Trees, lovely, and beautifull, eſpecially when we are in our Gallantrie; full of <hi>beautifull bloſſoms and pleaſant, wholſome Fruits;</hi> and ſome greedily pluck us, and tear us, and ſometimes breake off ſome of our Branches, to get our Fruits; and ſo go their waies; But ſpeake never a word to us; neither do they underſtand what we ſay to them, though we are continually ſpeaking to men, and are never weary, of inſtructing, and teaching man his Duty towards God, our Creator; and alſo praiſing, and ſetting forth his glory; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of our Creation; as thou knoweſt, and haſt often witneſſed the ſame on our behalfe.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:55886:56"/>
                  <head>Moſt people are ignorant, both of Gods word, and Works.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>I believe what yee ſay to be true; People (for the greateſt part of the world) are ignorant of God, of themſelves, and of all his Creatures; as well as ignorant of the Scriptures; Though God hath given us two great <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes or Books</hi> to read, and ſtudy; <hi>his word, and his Workes:</hi> yet people (ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally) are ignorant of both; ſottiſh children (as the Prophet calls them) who have no underſtanding: <hi>wherefore he that made them, will not have mercy on them, and he that formed them will ſhew them no fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour: Iſay</hi> 27.11.</p>
                     <p>Tremble at this word, yee <hi>ignorant ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh people;</hi> there is not any mercy for you, whilſt yee remain ignorant <hi>of God, of your ſelves, of his word, and of his workes.</hi> Therefore learn, and be inſtructed, elſe ye ſhall ſurely Periſh: the very <hi>Trees of the Garden,</hi> and <hi>all the Creatures of God,</hi> will witneſſe againſt you.</p>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:55886:56"/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlearned men may read in the Booke of the Creatures.</note> The <hi>illitterate man</hi> that knowes not a word, or a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Book, and thinks to be excuſed, becauſe he is not learned; yet he ſhall find it otherwiſe, one day; For this Book, of the Creatures is open, and legible by all men; As S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                        <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of the ignorant heathen Rom. 1. <hi>They ſhall be left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe,</hi> Becauſe the <hi>inviſible things of God</hi> (his <hi>Attributes,</hi> his <hi>Wiſdom, Power, and Goodneſſe, his Love, Bounty, and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> to all) are clearly ſeen in the things that he hath made: Therefore it concerns men to learn the <hi>voice, and Language of the Creatures of God,</hi> (and among them the <hi>voice, and language of Fruit-trees</hi>) as well as of his <hi>Word,</hi> and to obſerve their <hi>Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and instructions;</hi> for the mind, and things of God are ſeen clearly in them, though not ſo clearly as in his word; But being joyned, and conſidered together, we may learn our Duty to God; And in the doing thereof, We ſhall be bleſſed of him.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:55886:57"/>
               <head>Section 22.</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>An invitation, and incouragement to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with Fruit-trees.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>Come my Friends let us walke into this pleaſant Garden, and have ſome further Diſcourſe with thoſe <hi>innocent, harmleſſe Companions, the Fruit-trees;</hi> they will bid us welcome, and are ſtill ready, and at leaſure to conferre with us, and will be ſure to teach us one good Leſſon or other, But We muſt not forget what hath been often ſaid concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the way, and manner of their Diſcourſe with Men;</hi> That it is not audible to the <hi>outward ſence of hearing, in the ſound of words:</hi> but alwaies to the <hi>inward ſence,</hi> the <hi>mind, and understanding</hi> And thus they will Diſcourſe with us as long as we pleaſe, And they always ſpeake <hi>Rational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and Religiouſly;</hi> in every thing taking Gods part, ſpeaking to his <hi>praiſe, and glory;</hi> and for the inſtruction of all men; both for our <hi>Temporall, and Spirituall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Here is a very large Garden, full of Faire, and beautifull Fruit-trees, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:55886:57"/> we have both <hi>Profitt, and Pleaſure:</hi> but I have heard alſo there are many things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you occaſioning <hi>admiration</hi> in men; what things are they that may occaſion <hi>admiration,</hi> what ſay yee of your ſelves.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Many things in Fruit-trees occaſion admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>Thou maieſt ſee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things in the courſe of our Natures that may occaſion <hi>admiration</hi> of the <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Power, and goodneſse of God;</hi> 1: if thou do but take Notice of our <hi>Originall: and first springing up,</hi> we then lying wrapt up in ſmall ſeeds, each one no biger then a graine of Wheate, yet out of thoſe came theſe <hi>huge, and vast bodies</hi> that thou ſeeſt here above Ground; each one according to its own Nature; every ſeed keeping (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly) its own kind, and Nature: though many ſorts are ſowen in one bed of Earth, and drawing the ſame juyce of the earth yet each ſeede retaines its owne Nature.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Tender Fruits come forth with Covers upon them: the more hardy without.</note> And ſecondly: If thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the <hi>manner</hi> of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth our Fruits, (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially wee <hi>Aprecotts, Cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Plumbs,</hi> and ſuch as are
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:55886:58"/> of the moſt tender kinds) our Fruits come forth with <hi>Coates and Garments upon their backs;</hi> being ſo tender, that (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſame, they could not indure the common Aire: If thou obſerve thou maiſt ſee (in our knitting time) our <hi>infant Fruit</hi> within the Bloſſome, no bigger then a <hi>Pinns head;</hi> which increaſing, by little, and little tears this Coate, or Garment, and throwes it off; being then hardy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to endure the Aire: and ſo we grow on to ripeneſſe.</p>
                     <p>But we that are more <hi>strong, and hardy Fruits;</hi> (<hi>Apples, Peares</hi> &amp;c:) have no ſuch <hi>Coates, or Garments</hi> upon Us, when we are born, we are naked when we come firſt into the world; our Bloſſoms fall off from us, when firſt we begin to knit, and appear, and ſo we grow on to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>I perceve then hereby, That that which ſome Learned Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers call the <hi>Wiſdome of Nature,</hi> in take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Care of it ſelf in theſe things, is but the <hi>Courſe, and law of Nature:</hi> but is indeed the <hi>Wiſdome of the God of Nature:</hi> who as he hath made all Creatures, ſo he knoweth perfectly their ſeverall Natures; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly provideth for them.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:55886:58"/>
               <head>Section 23.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                  <p>Well: This is conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable in order to our <hi>admiration;</hi> But what other particulers can yee tell us of to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Different ſubstances made of one Subſtance.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>Take notice of, and conſider theſe particulers alſo; Will it not cauſe <hi>Admiration</hi> to ſee, and conſider how many <hi>ſeverall Substances</hi> are made of <hi>one Simple ſubstance:</hi> For of the <hi>Sap</hi> of Trees is made the <hi>Barke, Wood, Pith, Leaves, Buds, Bloſsoms, Stalks, Fruit, and Seed:</hi> drawne from the ſame juyce of the Earth.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Defferent Gifts and Graces, wrought by the ſame Spirit.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <p>This illuſtrates to us; that ſo it is in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things: the paralell holds good, the Variety of <hi>Gifts, and Graces</hi> in bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, proceede from <hi>one and the ſelf ſame Spirit;</hi> as we ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4. <hi>There are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities of Gifts, but the ſame Spirit: And diverſities of Administrations, but the ſame Lord, and ver.</hi> 6 <hi>diverſities of Operations, but it
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:55886:59"/> is the ſame God that worketh all in all.</hi> To one is given the <hi>word of wiſdome,</hi> to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>word of knowledge;</hi> to another the <hi>Gifts of healing,</hi> to another the <hi>working of Miracles;</hi> to another <hi>Propheſie;</hi> to another <hi>diſcerning of Spirits;</hi> to another <hi>divers kinds of Tongues;</hi> to another the <hi>interpretation of Tongues.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Every Gift ought to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved for the profitt of all.</note> But all theſe worketh that <hi>one, and the ſelfe ſame spiritt;</hi> dividing to every man ſeverally as he will: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12.</p>
                     <p>By all which we ſhould learne to owne, and love one another; and to be uſefull, and ſerviceable one to another; every one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Gifts, and Talents</hi> which God hath given unto them; Let nor the <hi>Rich</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe the <hi>Poore,</hi> nor the <hi>Poore</hi> envie the <hi>Rich;</hi> let not the <hi>wiſe, and Learned,</hi> diſpiſe the meaner ſort, who want what they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have, ſuch may have <hi>one Gift,</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which the <hi>wiſe, and Learned</hi> have not, which may be uſefull to the body; let not the <hi>Eye</hi> ſay unto the <hi>Hand,</hi> I have no neede of thee; Nor the <hi>Head</hi> to the <hi>Feet,</hi> I have no need of you: for thoſe Members of the body which ſeem more feeble are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.22.</p>
                     <p>The variety of <hi>Gifts, Graces, and endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi>
                        <pb n="81" facs="tcp:55886:59"/> that men have, are wrought by the <hi>ſame ſpirit;</hi> and for whoſe Glory they are to be uſed, and improved, and for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitt of all.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <head>Section 24.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                  <p>Proceede further, and tell us ſome other perticulars that may oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion our <hi>admiration,</hi> in the knowledge of them; for we know the works of God are <hi>marvelous, and wonderfull,</hi> and many of them paſt finding out; and therefore God is to be <hi>admired</hi> in them.</p>
               </sp>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Grafts, and Buds, aſſimilate the Sap of the Stocks.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>Conſider this further, That <hi>Grafts, and Buds,</hi> ſet upon ſtocks, that are of <hi>wild kinds, of bitter, harſh, and ſower kinds,</hi> theſe <hi>Grafts, and Buds,</hi> being of a ſweete, and pleaſant nature, and drawing, and feeding upon the <hi>ſower Sap,</hi> of thoſe <hi>wild stocks</hi> yet they do change, &amp; alter this ſower, and bitter Sap, (that they draw, and feede upon) into their own ſweete, and pleaſant Nature, and bring forth Fruits ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their owne Natures; And the badneſſe of the ſtocks cannot alter the goodneſſe of the Grafts; but according to
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:55886:60"/> the Law, and Courſe of Nature, (which all Vegetables do keepe from their firſt Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they do convert all their Sap, and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment which they draw, into their own properties, and bring forth Fruits accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
                     <p>And is not this a Marvelous thing, that a great and large ſtock (it may be 40. times and more, bigger then the Graft that's ſet upon it) ſhould not be able to change the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Graft, (or the Bud, that is much ſmaller) into it's owne kind, and Nature. This then muſt be concluded: That it is the innate, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecall forme of the Graft, and Bud that maintaines, and keepes, inviolable that Law of Nature, that the God of Nature at firſt Creation fixed in every individuall. Who alone is to be Praiſed, and Admired in theſe, and all his workes.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <head>Section: 25.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                  <p>What other perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars do yee diſcover in the proceſſe of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wherein God is ſeene, and diſcovers his Wiſdome, and infinite excellencies, that may occaſion his <hi>Praiſe, and Admiration;</hi> when knowne and obſerved.</p>
               </sp>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:55886:60"/>
                  <head>Every ſmall Bud contains the Nature of the whole Tree in it ſelfe.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                     <p>Know, and conſider this further, That <hi>every ſmall Branch</hi> or Twigg, upon the Trees, yea, the <hi>least Bud</hi> upon the leaſt Graft, or Twigg; doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in it the <hi>Nature and property of the whole Tree;</hi> Though one Tree have many Thouſands of Buds upon it; yet every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular has <hi>virtually, or potentially,</hi> the <hi>whole Tree</hi> in it ſelfe: though the <hi>Bud he never ſo ſmall,</hi> and the <hi>Tree never ſo great;</hi> This is evident by <hi>Inoculating the Buds</hi> of any Tree, continuall Experience proves they are the ſame, and bring forth the ſame Fruits, as the Tree from which they were taken.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                     <p>I grant this is a truth, and apparent to continuall Experience from yeare to yeare, and is a thing to be much <hi>Admired,</hi> that all the Properties of a vaſt, huge Tree, ſhould be united into ſo narrow a compaſs; as <hi>a ſmall Bud,</hi> ſmaller then a Graine of Wheate; Nay more: The Nature, and propertie of a great Tree (though as bigg as 2. or 3. men can fathom, with their hands joynd'd,) does lye in the <hi>Roote of that ſmall Bud;</hi> ſome of which are as ſmall as <hi>a Pinns point;</hi> this is proved: by
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:55886:61"/> Experience; Becauſe when that <hi>ſmall Roote</hi> happens to be left upon the wood, in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king off the <hi>Bud</hi> to inocculate (as ſometimes it is) <hi>ſuch a Bud</hi> does not grow, nor ſpring in the leaſt: the Principall part being left behind; which is analogous with the Roote of a Tree in Planting: without which it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not grow; And therefore ſuch as under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take this worke of <hi>Inoculating,</hi> looke well to this, that <hi>this ſmall Roote of the Bud,</hi> be in it when it is ſet on the ſtock.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The Properties of a Tree, are in every ſeede.</note> And further: This is alſo true: and a thing to be conſidered, and <hi>admired,</hi> That as the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, and Vertues of the whole Tree are in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Bud,</hi> ſo alſo they are in <hi>every ſeede, or kernell,</hi> that is in every one of the Fruits; that grow upon the Tree; But herein a Caution is to be obſerved; (which is not ſo in <hi>Buds, and Grafts,</hi> which alwaies bring forth the ſame in kind;) That is, The <hi>ſeeds,</hi> or <hi>kernells</hi> of any Tree ſowen, will produce the ſame in kind, <hi>in this ſence,</hi> that is; if we ſow the <hi>ſeede of an Appletree,</hi> it will be of the ſame ſpeties; it will bring forth <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletrees;</hi> ſo of the ſeede of <hi>Peretrees,</hi> or any other kind; But then theſe young Trees produced by the <hi>ſame ſeede,</hi> will yet bring forth <hi>variety; ſeverall ſorts of Apples,</hi> ſome
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:55886:61"/> 
                        <hi>better,</hi> ſome <hi>worſe;</hi> yet all of them <hi>Apples,</hi> of one ſort or other; And in that perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler alſo it is the more <hi>Admirable,</hi> That the <hi>ſeede,</hi> or <hi>kernells</hi> being alike; from one, and the <hi>ſame Tree,</hi> ſhould yee bring forth <hi>diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſorts of Fruits;</hi> yet all of them Apples too; but different in kinds.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The ſame flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ſeede brings forth variety.</note> So alſo it is in the <hi>ſeedes of flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers</hi> when ſowen: <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                              <desc>•…</desc>
                           </gap>e ſelfe ſame ſeede,</hi> brings forth <hi>different ſorts of flowers;</hi> ſome <hi>double,</hi> ſome <hi>ſingle,</hi> ſome one colour, ſome another: which is to be <hi>Admired,</hi> if conſidered: God in his infinite Bounty, and goodneſſe gives us va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of his good Creatures, as well for <hi>Pleaſure, and delight,</hi> as for <hi>Neceſſity.</hi> And this ſhould occaſion his <hi>Praiſe, and Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration;</hi> and more <hi>chearefull Service,</hi> from us, who reape the <hi>benifitt, and comfort thereof.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <head>Section 25.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                  <p>What other wonders in Nature are there, that we ſhould take notice of, in your continuall courſe, and proceſſe from yeare, to yeare, whereby you ſet forth the glory of the Creatour; that we may underſtand it, and Admire God in his workes: for <hi>the workes of the Lord are
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:55886:62"/> great ſought out of all them, that have plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure therein</hi> Pſ. 111.2, 3. <hi>His worke is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and gloriouſe:</hi> and Ver. 4. <hi>O come hither, and behold the workes of God, How wonderfull he is in his doings: He hath ſo done his Marvelous workes that they ought to be had in remembrance.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>FR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IT-TREES:</speaker>
                  <p>We diſcover many things to be taken notice of, and Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by all men; for the <hi>Eternall Power, and Wiſdome, goodneſse, and bounty of God</hi> is ſeene in us, beſides what has beene, or may be ſaid, take notice of this further.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Many kinds of Fruits up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one Tree.</note> Upon <hi>one great Appletree,</hi> (or any other kind) may be grafted <hi>many kinds;</hi> great <hi>variety;</hi> according to the number of the boughes, and Branches, ſo many ſeverall ſorts may be grafted, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps 20. 30. 40. or more, ſeverall ſorts of Apples; may be Engrafted upon the ſame Tree, if men deſire it, for a curioſity: ſome early kinds, ſome later: ſome of one ſhape and bigneſſe, ſome of another, the Grafts being variouſe, (though they grow all upon <hi>one Tree,</hi> and feede upon <hi>one, and the ſelfe ſame Sap,</hi>) yet they will bring forth <hi>variety of Fruits,</hi> every Graft, after his owne kind.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SBANDMAN:</speaker>
                  <p>I have ſeene variety
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:55886:62"/> of Fruits upon one Tree, and many more kinds might have beene Grafted upon it, if men would, theſe ſeverall ſorts of Grafts brought forth variety of Fruits, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Graft after his kind: And this proves that to be true which a Learned <note n="*" place="margin">Sr: Fran: Bacon: Nat: Hiſt: pag. 100.</note> Philoſopher hath aſſerted; That <hi>Grafts Governe; all Grafts Rule,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they are Engrafted upon a different ſtock, yet they convert that different Sap, which they feede upon, into their owne Natures, and bring forth Fruits accordingly.</p>
                  <p>And this obſervation may be uſefull, both for Profitt, and Pleaſure; A man that hath but a ſmall peece of ground for his Orchard, yet he may have variety of Fruits upon a few Trees; according to the bigneſſe, and largeneſſe of the Trees; ſo he may multiply his Grafts, of what kinds he thinks beſt.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Si quid novisti reſtius istis;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Candidus imperti: ſi non, his utere mecum.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:63"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55886:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
